WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
Welcome to
the finale of Survivor 42.
I love finale nights,
and I think tonight
is gonna be very exciting
and very unpredictable
because there are still
so many ways it could play out
and so many players who have
a legit shot to win.
There are only
two weapons left in the game--
Mike and Maryanne
both have idols.
They both have to play
them with five players left,
which means, in theory,
they both get to four.
Which means, in theory,
they're at least making fire--
which means at least one
of them is in the final three.
So for the other players,
it will come down
to immunity challenges,
because, without the necklace,
you are left to rely
on your ability
to persuade other players
that what you want
is what they need.
And that is very tough
to do on Survivor,
because both can't be true.
There's only one winner.
So tonight we're gonna have
two immunity challenges,
two Tribal Councils,
one fire-making showdown,
and then we will read the votes
here in beautiful Fiji
and go right into the aftershow
and talk about everything,
while the players are still raw
and hungry and dirty.
Take a look at this final five.
That's a final five.
You have Mike, Jonathan,
Romeo, Lindsay and Maryanne.
Three of them are gonna get
to the end to get a chance
to plead their case
about why they deserve
the title of Sole Survivor
and the million dollars
that goes along with it.
Here we go.
This is
the finale of Survivor 42.
Savagery is what's
gonna happen right now.
Don't get in my way.
I'm balls to the wall,
going all out.
I've never given up on anything.
On anything I've done,
I've gone extra.
And that's what I'm doing
right now.
I'm fighting
to the bitter end.
I want to show that I'm here
to play my game
and I'm here to win.
I can close the deal and
be the winner of Survivor 42.
In the end, I will be wearing
theSurvivor tiara on my head,
and I will be
the ultimate Mr. Survivor.
There's nothing
that's gonna stop me.
At the end of the day,
everyone will know
that Jonathan gave
everything that he had.
There's gonna be
a battle royale.
This is a big game.
I have to be a big player.
My goal is to win Survivor.
The million dollars is mine.
I don't want to be
second or third,
and I'm gonna take it all.
After Omar was voted out,
everybody was
just smiling and laughing.
Everyone's just happy
we've made it to the final five.
And then we come to find out
that we are now
at a brand-new beach.
Holy crap. I don't know
where we are, but this is it.
This is our home.
There's all our clothes.
Well, at least
we got a machete and a pot.
This is bizarre.
Is there more to look at?
I think this is it, guys.
We don't even have our tarp.
We're back at scratch.
Yeah.
Good news is,
we have only three days.
This new beach has nothing.
We don't have a tarp,
we don't have a shelter,
but you know what?
I was on cloud nine
because, by voting out Omar,
now everybody on the jury knows
Maryanne is here to play.
I might actually have a chance
to make it to the end
and win this thing.
And I haven't felt like that
this whole game.
It's all coming together.
Listen,
I have no hard feelings,
but I just want to know,
what did Omar tell you
to convince you to vote for me?
I never talked to Omar.
You weren't the plan.
Well, you voted for me.
I know, but I want
to hear what made you
pick Omar first.
So that's why...
Yeah, we-we, uh, we planned Omar
for a little bit.
Okay, and I'm your--
I'm in your alliance,
and I was unaware of that.
You voted for me, Lindsay.
But you already backed up
on your alliance,
because I'm supposed to be
aligned with you. And you...
So was Omar.
- You just... Well, you backed...
- You voted for me.
I'm so pissed.
Now I have to deal with
the stupid wrath of Jonathan
being all righteous of like,
"You voted for me.
You are the one
who are in the wrong."
Like, dude, screw you.
If you're telling me Omar
was the plan the whole time,
and I'm in your alliance,
you didn't tell me that.
That means you lied to me, too.
I think I've been
getting played this whole time.
No. You voted for me, Lindsay.
You're forgetting.
I can't stand
how he talks to me.
I'm frustrated
that I have to kiss his ass
and grovel,
just for the sake of getting
through the next few days.
And just this cockiness
that he now has
just drives me
up a frickin' wall.
I voted for you because
Omar pinned me against you.
But if I,
but if I knew the truth,
I wouldn't have...
[groans]
He's impossible
to talk to.
He's just so frickin' righteous,
and it drives me insane.
Well, since we're all
being honest here,
I have an idol, and I'm using it
in the next Tribal,
so at least I get to final four.
If you guys want to vote me out
after, that's fine.
Good for you, man.
Good for you.
You're playing your game.
I'm here
by the skin of my teeth.
They should just name me
- "The In-
- Case Survivor,"
because every time there's
a plan to vote somebody off,
somebody's always gonna
throw votes on Romeo.
Just in case that person plays
an idol, Romeo goes home.
So I thought the only way
that I can survive
the next Tribal Council
is to come up with this lie,
which is to say that I have
a hidden immunity idol.
Yeah.
They seem to buy it,
but just to be sure,
I made a fake idol.
And, uh, I came up
with this little baby.
See?
I think I did pretty good.
I suck at arts and crafts,
so my second grade teacher
would be very proud of me.
And, uh, hopefully it'll get me
through another Tribal Council.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
I want you.
I literally want you to win.
And, like,
Mike gave me his word.
He said, "If I'm here at five,
I'll give you the idol."
It will be
a two-three-two vote on Omar.
Then he's out.
- Yeah.
- Here's my promise to you, my giveback.
- Yeah. Mm-hmm.
I'm the only one with an idol left.
- Yeah.
- I will either give it to you if you want it...
...or play it for you.
- I got your back.
- Yeah.
- I give you my word, you'll be in the final four.
- Okay.
I'm in the worst position
I could possibly be in.
Romeo claims he has an idol.
Mike has an idol, and he's
never gonna turn on Jonathan.
And they're obviously gonna take
Maryanne to the end over me.
So if I don't win immunity
today,
I'm definitely going home.
I don't know about that.
Yeah, but you're not
gonna play that for me.
I know that every...
everyone wants me out.
Mike is saying that he might
play his idol for me,
but he told Maryanne he would
give her the idol at five.
So I'm like, "Don't lie to me."
I appreciate that.
Please don't.
I'm not. Look at me.
I'm not.
Listen, it's okay. Come here.
My vote's Romeo.
- Okay?
- Mm-hmm.
I'm not.
I'm trying to stay positive,
but if something doesn't happen,
I feel like I'm screwed.
Yes.
Whoa! Tree mail. Yeah.
"Another shot at immunity.
"Final four
is just one vote away.
"If you want
to increase your chances,
the riddle shows you the way."
One for you, Lindsay.
One for you, Mike.
We get tree mail today, knowing
that it's a final five immunity,
but we also get a little
envelope that's saying
"Final Advantage Clue."
And we're all like...
"First you must
unscramble the words,
"then decipher the phrase.
"You cannot search
for the advantage until
you have correctly solved and
written down the entire phrase."
Tree mail was a word scramble
to figure out a riddle,
which would tell us
where to find an advantage.
I suck at riddles,
I suck at puzzles, so I knew
that I wasn't gonna get it.
But as long as Jonathan
and Mike didn't get it,
I didn't really care.
I mean, get it, Lindsay.
Go for it.
Luckily,
I'm good at word scrambles,
and I'm good at riddles.
What you got?
- Okay.
The riddle, it was
"Good fortune is tucked
in the toes
of the sleeping giant."
So I ran around like a banshee.
I was everywhere on this island.
A sleeping giant. Tree's giant.
Sleeping means it fell.
I ran all around every
single path on this island.
I'm definitely on the hot seat,
for sure,
so I need this advantage.
But I looked everywhere,
and nothing.
I got "giant" for this word.
I got "toes." What do you got
for the first word?
"Tucked."
"Tucked... in... the... toes...
of the 'blank.'"
We need to figure that one out.
Lindsay scrambled
and she runs away.
But then Mike's like,
"Hey, yeah, guys,
let's all work together."
And I'm like, "Ugh!"
Like, I'm like,
"I guess I have to sandbag it,"
because I don't want
these guys to go
and find the advantage.
I want Lindsay
to find the advantage,
'cause I want
to go to the end with her.
The "P" word.
Dang it.
I had to have been gone
for at least 40 minutes.
I was all along
the entire beach,
climbing up a giant rock wall.
I looked everywhere.
Nothing really stood out,
didn't see it.
And then I thought
that that dead tree
would be a sleeping giant.
I don't know what else
would be some giant landmark
that sticks out.
And that's where I'm stuck.
Giant trees. Giant boulders.
Oh, my God.
Aw, man.
"Congratulations.
In..."
"In a season where
you had to earn everything,
"you have a slight advantage
in today's immunity challenge.
Good luck."
I thought I was going home. Like...
to have this and to earn my way
to the final four on my own
and not have to rely on anybody,
like, this is huge.
Did you get it?
So Lindsay came back into camp,
and she had the advantage.
And I was ecstatic for her.
"Congratulations.
"In a season where you had
to earn everything,
"you will have
a slight advantage
in today's immunity challenge.
Good luck."
Nice.
As much as I don't like
the spot that I'm in,
I do have faith in myself.
Like, I have
so much fire under my ass.
That résumé
is looking mighty fine.
I have nothing else to lose,
so screw it.
Savagery is what's
gonna happen right now.
And I'm balls to the wall,
going all out to win this today.
Come on in.
Hell yeah.
- Yes.
Come on,
how cool is this challenge?
This looks amazing.
- Badass.
Pretty epic.
- Yes!
I was dreaming for
a station challenge.
Dreaming!
Hell yeah.
All right. Shall we get
to your final five
immunity challenge?
- Yes.
- Mm-hmm.
Lindsay,
come to take the necklace.
This is amazing.
- Thank you.
- Yeah.
Once again,
immunity is back up for grabs.
For today's challenge,
you're gonna race
through a series of obstacles,
collecting puzzle pieces
along the way.
Once you have all the pieces,
you're gonna use them
to solve a circular puzzle.
First to finish wins immunity,
guaranteed a spot
in the final four,
which means, at the very least,
you'll be making fire
to get to three.
In addition, today
you're playing for a reward.
Want to know what you're playing for?
Yes.
First to finish will enjoy, back at camp,
- pasta.
- No. You guessed it.
- You guessed it.
- Spaghetti.
Garlic bread.
Garlic bread?
You want some meat sauce?
Yes.
Yeah, yeah. Sure.
- Yes!
- Yes.
- How about some cake?
- Yes!
- Yeah!
- Little salad?
- Yes!
- And red wine.
- Yeah!
Get your buzz on.
Losers, Tribal Council,
where somebody
will be voted out of this game
and fall this short.
Come this close.
It won't happen.
Big stakes.
- Get to it? Yes, sir.
- Yeah!
All right.
Jeff, I also have an advantage
I would like to tell you about.
Tell me.
All right.
I solved a riddle,
and I gained a final advantage,
which says that I will have
a slight advantage
in today's immunity challenge.
Yes. Okay, so here's how
it's gonna work.
Lindsay, while everybody else
will have to untie six knots
at every station...
...you will untie one knot.
- Nice!
- Wow.
It's a big advantage.
Should get you here
to the puzzle first.
- Then it's on you. All right.
- Cool.
Take your spots. We'll get
started. Good luck, everybody.
Yeah!
Nice.
All right, here we go.
For a guaranteed spot
in the final four.
Survivors ready.
Go!
This challenge is on.
Lindsay with the big advantage.
She has one knot,
which means
she should start getting
on these obstacles
faster than anybody else.
But Jonathan gets there first.
Lindsay is right behind.
Lindsay's back. Jonathan's back.
Got to put it on the nail.
There you go.
Jonathan heading back out.
Lindsay heading back out.
Mike struggling.
That's a tough one.
Some of these
are a little easier.
Some are very difficult.
Everybody's got to do
all of 'em.
Romeo through the first
obstacle. He's back.
Mike with his first bag.
Jonathan back
with his second bag.
Here comes Lindsay, struggling.
She's got the rope.
She's across.
You're good.
Lindsay with her second bag.
Jonathan's
got his six knots undone.
Wow! That was quick.
Jonathan is on fire.
Third bag.
Ripping through this.
Mike's back with another bag.
Lindsay's across.
Tearing up those knees.
Come on, Maryanne.
- Keep digging.
- Okay.
Drop those planks when you're done.
Here comes Romeo.
Maryanne's across.
Here comes Jonathan.
Lindsay's across, quickly.
There you go.
Another bag for Lindsay.
Here comes Mike,
one rope at a time, hanging on.
Jonathan using those planks.
On his feet, not even crawling.
It's a lot of balance.
That is dangerous.
He's going for it.
Here comes Romeo.
He's going again.
Mike's across.
He's got another bag.
Maryanne, back on her hands and knees,
taking on
another tough obstacle.
Here comes Lindsay.
She's now in the lead.
Lindsay with one bag left.
Here comes Romeo.
He's got another bag.
Jonathan back with another bag.
Jonathan down to two bags left.
Here goes Lindsay.
Lindsay with her sixth
and final bag.
Maryanne is back
with another bag.
Jonathan heading
back with his fifth bag.
Wow!
Jonathan ripped
through that obstacle.
Lindsay drops.
Got to go back and start again.
And that is a big setback.
That will eat up the advantage
she had from this morning.
Mike with his fourth bag.
Here comes Romeo,
balancing,
reaching for that rope.
Here comes Mike.
Mike banging up those knees
to get here fast.
You're good, Mike.
Romeo with another bag.
Jonathan is eating
this challenge up right now.
- Here comes Maryanne, Jonathan. Little collision.
- Oh.
That's how you do it
on Survivor.
Jonathan back with all his bags.
Jonathan first to the puzzle.
Start working on it.
Lindsay's back now.
She can start working
on her puzzle.
It is Jonathan and Lindsay.
A very familiar sight
in challenges.
These two showing down
next to each other.
Here comes Romeo.
He's fighting to stay in this.
Romeo with his fifth.
He's got one left.
Maryanne's back
with another bag.
Mike is back.
He can start
working on the puzzle.
Lindsay trying to get a piece.
Jonathan trying
to find a piece.
This is a difficult puzzle,
as you would expect
on day 24 and final five.
Romeo, drop those planks.
Let's go!
Maryanne with her final bag.
You're good.
We're going to have everybody
on the puzzle on day 24.
Five players left.
One's going to be guaranteed
a spot in the final four.
Lindsay off to a fast start
on the puzzle.
Jonathan right there with her.
It is very close right now.
Mike would like to get in it
with his first piece.
Jonathan with another piece.
It is Jonathan and Lindsay
almost identical puzzles.
It's been one of the best
matchups we've seen on Survivor.
Often coming down
to Lindsay and Jonathan.
But Mike, Maryanne and Romeo
would like to change that up.
Spoiler. Spoiler. Yeah.
Mike with another piece.
It is Mike now in the lead.
Jonathan and Lindsay
trying to keep up.
Lindsay finds one that fits.
It is now Lindsay and Mike,
with Jonathan
and Maryanne trailing.
Romeo right where he started.
- Nothing.
- I suck at puzzles, Jeff.
Don't say that.
You always have a chance, Romeo.
Jonathan's been stuck
in the same spot for a while.
Lindsay with another piece.
Mike with another piece.
A little momentum going now.
Lindsay right on his tail.
Mike with another piece,
extending his lead.
Mike can feel it now.
He can see it starting
to come together.
Now he's got the outside
of the circle complete.
It's just the guts.
Lindsay with another piece.
Lindsay is still in this.
This is not over.
This is Mike and Lindsay
right now.
Mike has the advantage.
And another piece by Mike.
Lindsay trying to find one.
It's a big one.
Does it fit?
It does.
Lindsay with another piece.
Mike being very careful
with that puzzle.
You get too aggressive,
it could fall apart.
Meanwhile,
Lindsay picking up the pace.
She's got another piece.
Mike has been on the same piece
for a long time,
trying to get it in there
without knocking anything over.
That's opening the door
for Lindsay, and she is
taking advantage of it.
Mike's got it in.
Lindsay's now the one
losing time,
trying to wedge a piece in.
Mike with another piece.
He's down to five pieces.
Lindsay now starting
to fall apart.
It's losing its shape.
She can feel it.
That's a scary spot.
Lindsay's got it in.
She's back in business.
Got to pick up the pace again.
Lindsay with another piece.
We are dead even right now.
Mike and Lindsay--
five pieces each.
Both trying to wedge a piece in.
Mike has his piece in.
Mike is down
to four now.
Lindsay now down
to four pieces.
Michael with another piece.
This couldn't be any closer.
Mike with another piece.
He's down to two pieces.
Lindsay with another piece.
This could come down to seconds
between Mike and Lindsay.
Mike's got another piece.
He's down to his last piece, but
he's got to get it in without
destroying everything else,
and that will take a second.
Mike working it.
He's using his whole body
to hold the puzzle together,
which is what you have to do.
Lindsay down to two pieces.
Lindsay has another piece.
- Jeff! Jeff! Jeff! Jeff! Jeff!
- Mike has it!
- Yes! Yes!
- Mike pulls it out by one piece!
Come on! Jeff!
Mike going to the final four!
- Yeah!
What a finish. Wow.
I've been waiting 21 years
for this.
Whoa. One piece away, Lindsay.
Man, my kids are going
to be proud right now.
Holy crap, Jeff. Wow.
I've been waiting 21 years
for this.
Jeff, look at it.
- That's good, right?
- Look at that.
- Those are points in Hoboken.
- In Hoboken, those are points.
- Those are points.
Those are well-earned
Survivor scars.
This is what you got right here.
Oh, I bet they are.
- Yeah? Yeah?
- Yeah.
- My man!
- 21 years.
Yeah. Badass.
- So tell me about that.
Because it... You can just
say that, but that means,
from season one,
you've been watching.
Season one,
I watched in the firehouse.
And for me to be here now
standing with Jeff Probst with
an immunity necklace
around my neck,
again
with these great competitors,
- and I'm sitting up here at the end?
- You killed it.
- Give me a hug. Thank you, man.
- You got it, man.
- Congratulations.
- Thank you so much.
Here's where things stand.
You are guaranteed a spot
in final four.
That means,
at the very least,
you're making fire
for a shot at three.
Jonathan, Maryanne,
Romeo, Lindsay,
tonight one of you--
the dream will end.
You'll go to the jury.
It will not be you. You've also
- earned pasta.
- I forgot about that.
- Yeah. Garlic bread, cake.
- Oh, my God.
Choose one person to join you.
So think
about what you're doing.
You're fueling your competition
or you're buying favor.
Actually, I'm deciding
about buying favor.
There's somebody here
that's been dizzy every day.
He started at 250.
He's down to, like, 210.
He's got nothing left
in the tank.
And I love you guys.
I just think, right now,
he hasn't had a reward in a while.
Of course.
And I got to bring Jonathan.
I love you, bro.
Jonathan will be joining...
- Want to give me another one?
- No.
- Okay. All right.
- That's it.
Maryanne, Romeo, Lindsay,
got nothing for you.
Grab your stuff,
head back to camp.
- See you tonight at Tribal.
- Thank you.
Thank you. Oh.
Ugh! So close!
Being
one piece away?
It just sucks, but I'm not going
to quit. I'm not going
to stop playing because
people don't want me there.
Screw that.
I'm making it to the end,
and I'll apologize later.
- Thank you.
- Look at this!
- Thank you, God, and thank you, Mike. Ah!
- Oh, my God.
Vanilla cake.
Oh, Mike, give me a hug!
Ah!
Holy crap.
I was one piece.
I had one piece left.
Jonathan didn't even
keep doing the puzzle.
He just watched Mike do it.
Like, such a cocky ass.
Cheers to our brotherhood.
History will be made with us.
There are good ships,
there are bad ships,
but there are no ships
like friendships.
That's a good one.
And to just have him,
like, be able
to gloat about me leaving
before him just, like, irks me
because I'm a way better player
than Jonathan.
Mmm.
Today at the immunity challenge,
I won this necklace.
I'm playing against
kids that are 30 years younger
than me.
Two of them have been
immunity beasts.
And Lindsay had
a distinct advantage today,
and I still won immunity,
and it feels unbelievable.
I have a little bit of power.
You have a lot of power,
brother. Come on, dude.
I have immunity.
Plus, I have an idol
in my pocket.
Now I got to figure out
what I'm gonna do with it,
which I'm not exactly sure yet.
I just know that I'm gonna
play it for somebody and take
who I want to the final four.
Romeo's saying he has an idol.
We got to take away
our biggest threat.
The plan tonight is
to get Lindsay out.
She is an absolute beast.
She's really good at puzzles.
She's physically strong.
She's got a good head
on her shoulders. She talks.
So she's somebody
that you don't want
to be sitting by
in the final three.
I just feel like
they're coming after me, Mike,
'cause you know they're talking
about me right now.
Of course they are, but, dude,
you're not going home tonight.
- I got one favor to ask of you.
- Uh-huh.
If she pulls an idol,
will you play it on me?
That would help.
So give me... give me your word
right now, please.
I don't have to save you. I
swear on this. I'm telling you.
Okay.
I don't know how the hell
I'm gonna make it out of here.
He's gonna give his idol to Jon.
Exactly.
No.
He gave me his word.
He gave me his word
about stuff, too,
and it means nothing.
Today was a challenge
that I absolutely needed to win.
So now the only possible way
that I'm going
to get through this is to
vote for Jonathan--
all three of us--
and hope that Mike
gives his idol
to either myself or Maryanne.
He gave me his word that he
would play his idol for me.
Did he give you the same word?
He kind of said it to me
on the beach that he might.
He didn't guarantee it.
I really, truly do think
Jonathan won't be here tomorrow.
I have faith.
Maryanne is
extremely confident that
Mike is going
to play his immunity idol
for her,
but I can't rely on that.
So my plan is to pitch
to Mike hard
to make him feel
extremely guilty
that he'd be breaking his word
if he didn't pick me.
So, I'm just begging
to not go home.
I valued how much
that you feel like your word,
as long as someone shows trust
back, you show trust to them.
I feel like I very much
earned that with the trust
that I've given you.
We had a bond--
you, me, and Omar--
we're going
to make it to the end.
Omar burned you,
but I stayed true to my word,
and you saying to me,
"I would love to see you get
- to the end."
- That's still true.
- But you have the power of that.
- I know. Yeah.
So if I leave,
then it makes me feel
that that was a lie.
It's not a lie.
I still feel that way.
Honestly, I love Lindsay.
I think she's a great girl.
I really do.
I see my own daughter in her.
I think she got caught up
in the wrong place
and with the wrong person.
Other than that,
she's been loyal to me.
But on the other hand, it's fair
that I protect Jonathan
'cause he protected me,
and Maryanne has been a person
of good character.
She's kept her word,
and that means a lot to me.
I'm gonna tell you my dilemma.
When that happened with Omar
- and-and you, I thought...
- Mm-hmm.
...I went to Maryanne
and made a promise to her.
Then this is what's hard
for me, Mike,
because I feel like
I've proven myself to you
in so many ways, and now,
because you now made
a last-minute promise
to Maryanne, everything
that I did meant ....
No, that's not true.
Mike, look at me in my eyes.
I 100% never lied to you once.
I promise you, I swear
- on everything.
- I believe you. Yeah.
I had your back
and told you everything.
And this is your time
to-to show me the trust back.
I'm very torn. I...
Honestly,
I don't have my-my mind made up.
I've put myself
in a position where
I have to make a decision
that's going to
hurt somebody,
and it sucks.
I'm not 100% any way right now.
But now I got to figure out
what's the right thing to do.
Right, he's got to... You know
what, though? You're right.
But listen.
I... Like, my mind says, like,
I think I can squeeze it out.
Right now
Lindsay is a sitting duck, but
not only do I have my idol,
which is
the only secret that has been
kept in this entire game,
but also Mike might give
his idol to me at Tribal.
So this means that my idol--
I can use it to save Lindsay
and blindside Jonathan.
The question is,
what gives me
my best chance of winning?
Emotionally, yes.
Lindsay's played
such a great game.
She's won immunities
and taken major risks,
and the jury loves that.
But voting out someone
who knows they're going home--
that's not a big move.
But if I play my idol
on Lindsay
and blindside Jonathan,
the jury will know
that I am here to play
and that I'm a contender.
But it all comes down
to what Mike does,
and this could make
or break my game.
Let's start this morning.
Lindsay, you wake up,
and you each have a riddle
to solve.
Walk me through what happened.
We each get this envelope
that says,
you have
to fix the word scramble.
Once you figure that out,
you're off to the races
to solve the riddle
and find a secret advantage.
And I was the only one
who solved the riddle.
- I-I had to have been gone for at least 40 minutes.
- At least.
Jonathan, it's got
to be frustrating
because it's an advantage.
It's offering you something
in the game
if you can just solve it.
Yeah, that's the thing.
I haven't felt normal
in days, Mr. Jeff,
because of how hard
this has been.
It took four people.
- Yeah.
- No, we didn't get it.
- And we still didn't get it.
No, Lindsay had
to come back and tell us.
Yeah. We said... we said,
"Lindsay, can you tell us
what it was?" She's like,
"Well, yeah, I got it now."
- It was "sleeping."
- It was "sleeping." It was "sleeping."
It was "sleeping."
We look at the word.
We said, "We can't believe
it was 'sleeping.'"
So, Lindsay, you get
the advantage, but did you feel,
going into the challenge,
that that advantage
would be helpful?
Absolutely. I knew
if I didn't win, I'm going home.
And I was one puzzle piece short
from beating Mike.
Super happy for Mike.
Really proud of him
that he got it.
Just sucks
that in return of that,
I'm most likely going home.
So what's giving you
that feeling?
Based on last Tribal.
Everyone else,
apparently, already kind of knew
that Omar was working everybody.
I didn't until afterwards.
And then there was a lot
of damage control to do,
and some that wasn't able
to be repaired, it seems.
Jonathan, then,
what was the vibe at camp?
I thought it would be fireworks
with people running around
everywhere. Was it not?
Is everybody locked in
that it's Lindsay?
Uh, you can never know
for sure,
of course, because then
comfort sets in,
and we know that
that kills people in this game.
But people do recognize Lindsay
as a big threat, which she is.
Maryanne, what was your take
on what was going down at camp?
In my perspective,
I had to decide
on whether I wanted
to vote emotionally
on who I feel
I want it to be in the end,
and strategically on who
I feel is the best combination
of people to have in the end.
And everyone here knows that
I wear my heart on my sleeve,
so that was something that
was difficult for me because
I love every single person here,
and I...
but I need to go and recognize
that, like,
I want to play this game for me,
and that means
that I might have
to, like, go back on my word,
or, like, that means
that I might have to go back
on an alliance, and that sucks.
So, Lindsay, do you feel
that you were the only one that
was openly feeling desperate?
- Yes.
- So that was clear to everybody?
Yeah, so it's calm
because no one has
to really make a decision.
It was more me having
to plead my case of why
I would like to stay.
I mean, on one end,
I got deceived by Omar
this entire time,
so my social game clearly sucks,
strategic game sucks, because
all I have
is my competitive edge.
That's only one...
That's one note.
So, in terms of fighting
against the jury,
that's not really a big case.
That's only one end of that.
No, absolutely not.
Every time Lindsay
communicates with people,
they have a bond with her.
It's not just
because you got tricked
that makes you
a bad social player at all.
You're social with everyone,
and everyone loves you.
And that's the truth.
And so, Lindsay,
this is a question
I can never figure out
what I would do.
How do you stop trying?
Because I'm sure, at some point,
you go, "Well, okay, I guess
that's it. But wait, Mike,
let me just... Can I...? Let me
just try it one more time."
- Is that what happened?
- That's literally what I did.
- That's exactly what happened. Yes.
- Okay.
I'm doing it right now. Like,
I have to just pitch my case
as best as I can.
Until you snuff that torch
and my name is up there,
I have to just hope
that I can just say one
last thing and offer one last...
I don't know. I-I don't know.
It's like guns blazing,
whatever I have left.
I'm just throwing anything
out there.
Jonathan, how do you feel about
that aspect of the game
in this sense?
The better player you are,
the more likely
you are to be taken out.
In theory, in a lot of games,
the better player you are,
the more likely you are to win
'cause you're better.
It's a fine line. If you aren't
a great player, then
people want
to keep you till the end, but
if you're looked at
as too strong, then done.
Or finding the person
or people
that you really can trust,
and they... you work together
to get to the end,
even if you're a good player,
that helps out.
But again, it is Survivor.
That changes quickly.
And what does that mean?
That you can be a good player,
and if you find
another good player
that you trust,
then maybe the two of you bond
and you protect each other?
Yeah. You don't even have
to be two good players.
Just two people that really know
that they have
each other's back.
As long as one of them
doesn't feel
the other one has an upper hand,
you kind of work together.
I mean,
but it's a hard thing to find.
Well, Maryanne, the key is,
you have to align with people
that you believe you can beat,
and the trick is,
they're aligning with you
because they believe
they can beat you.
Exactly, and so many people have
tried to play that fine line
and played it a little too well.
That's truly why I think
Omar is there, because he...
I thought I was his number one,
but then
I realized that if I did take
my number one to the end,
I'd be taken
and herded as a goat.
But you have to realize,
"Okay, no. I have
"to go, and I now have
to find new allies
"who are round the same level
as me
so I actually have a chance
to win at the end."
So, Romeo, if you were gonna
give this vote a title,
this chapter is called what?
What's the vote about?
I would call it "The Fighter."
Whoever it is didn't give up.
They kept fighting till the
very end, and that's admirable.
So, Lindsay,
you think he's talking to you?
It's "Lindsay: The Fighter"?
Yeah, but I-I like that title.
I'm cool with it.
If-if the reason
for me leaving is because
no one thinks they can beat me,
that's the best way
for me to leave.
All right, well, it sounds
like it is time to vote.
Romeo, you're up.
All right, if anybody has
an advantage or an idol,
and you want to play it,
now would be the time to do so.
Jeff.
I waited 21 years
to do this, also.
However, I can't play it
for myself,
but I want to repay
somebody's loyalty to me.
I'm gonna play this
for Maryanne, okay?
You deserve it. I want you
to be here tomorrow.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
This is a hidden immunity idol.
Any votes cast
for Maryanne will not count.
Jeff?
Um, I will...
not be playing this
for myself because
it is a fake idol.
I made it at camp. So I'm going
to throw it in the fire.
Good for you. Good for you. Okay.
All right, I'll read the votes.
First vote-- Lindsay.
Jonathan. One vote-- Lindsay,
one vote-- Jonathan.
Lindsay. Two votes-- Lindsay,
14th person voted out
of Survivor 42-- Lindsay.
It's three. It's enough.
Need to bring me your torch.
It was fun
while it lasted, guys.
Love you, girl.
Good luck.
- I love you so much.
- Good luck to you.
Ugh.
Lindsay, the tribe has spoken.
Time for you to go. Ah.
- Good luck, guys.
- Bye, Lindsay.
I'm gonna eat so much food!
Enjoy it.
All right, you've made it
to the final four.
Tomorrow you'll compete in
your final immunity challenge.
Grab your torches,
head back to camp.
Good night.
Thanks, Jeff.
I love that the label's
"The Fighter," and I like
that that's my tagline
for this because I really felt
like I fought my way
throughout this whole game.
And I'm incredibly proud
of myself
of how far I got.
This was so much fun.
I got to experience
so many Survivor things
that so many people
don't get to have.
Of course,
I'm a little upset right now,
but this was the best ever.
Come on in.
I can hear you breathing just
walking up the steps, Maryanne.
Oh, yeah.
Good morning, Jeff.
Good morning, Mr. Jeff.
Good morning.
Oh, wow.
It is a Survivor classic.
- You know the name?
- Yes, sir.
All right, so,
let me just check in.
How are you doing, day 25?
Mike, what are you feeling?
Obviously we're very depleted.
It's day 25.
But I always say,
"Big games, big players."
And that's when you reach deeper
than you've ever reached
into everything you have
and put it out there,
and this is
the last immunity challenge.
And whatever's left in the tank,
you have to leave right here
on this platform today.
How about you, Romeo?
When you're about
to take on this challenge,
who all do you think of?
Do you draw
on inspiration right now?
Definitely. Family back home.
All the strong, independent
women that I coach back home.
They're looking at me
and saying, "Hang in there.
You know, you taught me
to push for what you want."
And now I'm showing them that
I'm pushing for what I want.
I want final three.
How about you, Jonathan?
What do you draw on right now?
We've been working this hard
for this moment, Mr. Jeff.
And for me
it comes down to this.
And everything that I have, I'm
going to pour it into this game,
and I'm going to give it my all
so that if I do get kicked off,
then I'll say,
"Hey, I fought the good fight.
I did everything I could do."
Maryanne, right now
you've been so vocal all season
of sharing your emotions.
You even say,
"I wear 'em on my sleeve."
What are you feeling right now?
What are you drawing on
to get you pumped up?
Um... right now...
I'm sorry.
I'm right now
drawing on knowing that
my whole family's going to be
watching me doing this, and...
one of my family members
is not talking
to the rest of my family,
so we haven't really
been together
for more than a year,
and it hurts.
But to know that at this moment,
even if they're separate,
we're together right now,
cheering me on
is the thing that's driving me
and pushing me.
So you being on Survivor
could bring your family back?
I want it more
than a million dollars, Jeff.
than a million dollars.
How do you now take that emotion
and turn it into energy
rather than sorrow or sadness?
I sit in the sorrow and sadness.
It's okay to feel sad,
but the thing is,
sadness doesn't take you anywhere.
It's what you do with that.
What am I going to do
with my sadness?
I'm going to turn it
into passion and drive
so that I push myself,
and I do the best that I can,
and I win this competition.
All right,
all four of you feel very ready.
You know what's driving you.
Let's get to it.
First things first, Mike.
Jeff, you might have to wrestle
me for this. I don't know.
- Ah, I don't want to wrestle you, man.
- Ah.
- I want love.
- You always get love, brother.
- Thank you.
It comes down to this, Mr. Jeff.
It comes down to this.
- Man, I'm stoked!
Come on!
For the last time,
immunity is back up for grabs.
For today's challenge,
you're going
to have one hand tied
behind your back.
You're going
to drop a ball down the chute.
It's going to spiral around.
You're going to catch it.
You're going to drop it again.
At regular intervals,
we will add another ball,
making it more difficult.
If at any point a ball drops,
you're out.
Last person left standing
wins immunity,
guaranteed a spot
at the final three
where you will get a shot
to plead your case to the jury
that you helped vote out,
why you deserve
the title of Sole Survivor
and the million dollars.
Plus, you decide,
"Who do I take with me
to put in that second seat, and
who do I force to make fire?"
All the power will be
in the hands
of the person
who wins this challenge.
Never has a challenge been
more important
in this season
than this one right here.
Are you ready?
Yes.
- Yes, sir.
Let's get to it.
Yes.
All right, everybody pick up
your first ball.
Here we go. Final four.
Win this, you're in three. Everybody,
drop your first ball.
This challenge is on.
Everything riding right here
on this beautifully-designed,
hypnotic game.
What started
as an art department project
in Survivor: China by somebody
who had some free time
on his hands, named Simo,
turned into a challenge
that we used
in Survivor: Tocantins,
and is now worth
a million dollars to somebody.
Right now you're just getting
warmed up,
getting a feel of this.
Mike drops.
Mike, you're out.
Mike is out with one ball.
Unbelievable.
Never seen that happen.
Mike has no control tonight.
I'm still in shock. What happened?
So am I.
Took my eye off of it
to put it in.
I mean,
we're in the warmup phase.
I literally had it in my hand.
It slipped out of my hand.
All right, we're down to three.
In a moment you're going
to add a second ball,
and that's when this challenge
will really start to kick in.
You'll have 15 seconds to do it.
You don't need to rush.
You just saw, with Mike,
how quickly it can be over.
Stay engaged.
Your 15 seconds starts now.
Maryanne drops.
Jonathan drops.
Romeo drops.
Everybody now
with two balls in motion.
The key to this challenge
is that gate.
It's going to send one ball
to the right,
and then the next ball
to the left.
It's going to come down
to the spacing.
That sound is hypnotic.
You got to stay very engaged.
Mike still stunned.
You never know what is going
to get you on Survivor.
Oh, Maryanne drops.
Maryanne is out, and now,
quickly, we are down to two.
And we only have two balls
in play.
It speaks to mental exhaustion.
This is not a difficult phase
of this challenge.
Lots of kids watching
could do this.
But they've been sleeping
and eating.
Mike and Maryanne--
their fate will be decided
by either Jonathan or Romeo.
Whoever wins this challenge
will hold
all the power tonight
at Tribal Council.
You're gonna get ready
to place a third ball.
You'll have 15 seconds
starting now.
Based on what's happened so far,
three balls might be it.
Romeo drops.
Jonathan drops, and we're now
into the next phase--
three balls.
Those balls now feel like
they're spinning more quickly.
That spacing is really critical.
Every part of you is focused
on one thing--
left, then right.
Left, then right.
This is it.
Who will have the power tonight
to try to control what happens?
Romeo and Jonathan,
if you hear a thud
of that ball hitting the plank,
that's going to echo
in your mind for a lifetime
if you lose Survivor.
All right, in a moment, we're
going to add a fourth ball,
and it's going
to get very difficult.
So you need to start thinking
about where you want
to put that fourth ball.
You'll have 15 seconds
to do it
starting now.
You can drop any time
in that window.
Romeo drops.
Jonathan drops.
Jonathan drops, and he's out.
Can't make the transition.
Romeo wins
his first individual immunity,
and it could not have come at a bigger time.
Romeo is in charge
of everything tonight.
Congratulations.
- Wow. What a challenge.
- On any given day...
- I'm proud of you. Great job.
...anybody can win anything.
You have the inspiration
in your heart.
Romeo, what is it right now?
I want to know right now.
I feel like I've been at the
bottom of this game for so long,
and I've just been hanging on
by my fingernails.
Every Tribal, my name comes up.
Every single Tribal,
Romeo was always the "in case."
In case somebody pulls an idol,
throw some votes on Romeo.
It's just... it's exhausting.
I've been fighting so hard,
and this feels good.
And I'm going to go back home,
and to all those young women
that I work with
and tell them, "That's what
I tried to teach you.
"Just-just don't give up
because, hey,
you could be in the final three
of Survivor."
This is a dream come true.
Let me come to you.
- Yeah!
- Great job.
- Jeff.
- Final four immunity.
You are not only safe.
Every decision that happens
tonight will be yours.
All right, everybody, grab
your stuff, head back to camp.
I will see you tonight
for the biggest Tribal
- of the season. Congrats.
- Thank you.
See you, Jeff.
Great job, man. Hey.
It was
extremely emotional for me
because I felt like, after
winning this, for the first time
in a long time, I had security.
This is definitely
my Miss America moment. The
spotlight's going to be on me.
I have the shiniest dress.
I have the most expensive dress
and the most coveted dress, so
we'll see what I do tonight.
Good job, Romeo.
Way to come through
when it counted, brother.
Thank you, guys.
Coming back from the challenge,
I felt like
MVP, Miss Universe
and prom queen all combined.
I beat Jonathan in the final
immunity challenge.
I am just thrilled,
and I think this necklace looks
a lot better on me
than it does
on big-ass Jonathan.
All good.
This big victory going into
one of the most important
Tribal Councils--
it's just kind of like vengeance
for all those horrible Tribals
where people just dismissed me
and-and just threw my name
out there just in case.
So it feels amazing,
and I'm enjoying it.
Oh, Romeo, unless you have
your mind made up, and you want
- to say something, I'd like to talk to you first.
- Sure.
- Hey, I'll talk to everybody...
- Has nothing to do with...
It has nothing to do
with strategy.
It's about my personal feeling.
Romeo has to send me
to make fire because
it's the consensus
that I'm the most dangerous.
It's a compliment and a curse.
It is what it is.
I think I can beat Maryanne.
Jonathan could be
a different story, though.
I'm in deep water,
but I didn't drown yet.
I know you're gonna have
to ask me to make fire.
I want you to know
that there's no animosity.
If I'm being 100% honest,
I know I'm the right move.
You'd be silly not to send me.
- That's why I know it's going to happen.
- I respect that a lot.
You need to think
about the other two.
- -
- If I go against Jonathan...  Yeah.
...and I beat Jonathan,
then you have to deal
with me and Maryanne.
- That's true.
- But if you make me make fire
against Maryanne
instead of Jonathan,
- you only got to deal with one of us.
- Yeah.
I do have to send Mike
to make fire,
but he has a good point.
If he goes against Jonathan
and he beats Jonathan,
now I'm going to be going
against the two most likable
people in the final three--
Mike and Maryanne.
You need to make a bold move.
That's up to you.
- Listen, I'm giving you advice. I'm just telling you...
- Yeah.
- that's how I would think about it.
I'm weighing everything
at this point
because what good would it do
for me
to get to the top three
and end up
third place or second place?
I want to win.
Jonathan, are you ready?
- Yes.
- Go.
Oh, that's a good amount.
- Oh, nice. Whoa!
- Hold on.
Jonathan is
very good at making fire,
and my fire-making, I would say,
is decent, but the thing is,
you never know what's going
to happen at Tribal.
Maybe I'm going to choke.
Maybe Mike is like,
"I'm a super good fire maker."
So, the best thing
for me is for Romeo
to put Jonathan and Mike
for fire,
and Jonathan wins.
You're good.
You just have to focus on, like,
building a fast teepee up,
'cause the trick is
to get the sticks to catch.
- They're caught. Mm-hmm.
- Once the sticks catch, you've won.
- So the sticks are caught. Do you see that?
- Then you're good.
I've been telling Jonathan
all the tips
and tricks to go
and make fire because
I don't want Mike here
in the final three with me.
I want Jonathan and Romeo
because that is my best shot
at winning.
- So, what was that? Like, 30 seconds?
- Yeah, that was, like,
surprisingly fast.
Jon, do you want
to go talk, my brother?
- Yeah, I do.
- Look at you practicing, huh?
You don't need practice.
I need practice now.
The first thing you do to
prepare for a night like tonight
is you start a lot of fires.
So I've been starting
a lot of fires.
And I've been
starting 'em quick,
but no one has seen Mike
make a fire.
I'm gonna try like hell to beat
your ass tonight in fire.
- You better, man. If you don't...
- Hey...
- If you don't, I would be ashamed.
- I get one last...
I got...
I got one last little bit in me.
- I hope... I hope you try.
- Oh, I'm definitely gonna try.
I ain't giving it to you.
If you want it,
you got to take it off me.
Be honest. You start fires
a lot, don't you?
- I don't know.
- Ah, yes, you do.
- Ah.
- I think that you've been dealing with fire too long
for you not
to be a good fire-starter.
I'll tell you what, though.
If Romeo gives you an out
not to make fire,
take it.
- Yeah?
- Yes.
Don't lose your spot.
I'm telling you.
- Yeah.
- Listen, you'll be the favorite,
definitely, to beat me,
but don't risk your spot
for that, man.
- I'm telling you right now.
- Yeah.
I know Mike's plan,
and I know what he's doing.
He's trying to get in my head.
I'm being serious.
If he gives you the out,
take it.
Mike, that's not going to work
for me, buddy.
I love you,
but you can't get in my head.
You're just going
to get me hyped to beat you.
This is exactly what I wanted.
We need him, like, spooked.
He's practicing right now.
He doesn't know if he's going
against his buddy or you,
and I want to keep it that way. Okay.
I can't sit down and relax
and be comfortable.
I have to be prepared to make
fire, because, in the end,
Romeo has all the power.
He might blindside me,
and I might have
to make fire against Mike.
'Cause the trick is,
you just want to get
the tiny sticks to ignite
'cause once you have
those tiny sticks ignited...
- Yeah.
- ...it's game over.
For 21 years,
I've been watching Survivor.
I always had one dream
in my life.
The last thing that I would
want to put on the top
of my résumé of life-- and
I have a pretty good résumé--
it would be to win Survivor.
So tonight,
whether I have to make fire
against Maryanne or Jonathan,
there's only one choice--
for me to win.
My fate is in my own hands,
and I truly feel that if I win
at making fire tonight,
I will win a million dollars.
So,
this is for me to lose.
All right, let's talk
about the past couple of days.
If you start yesterday morning,
you had a riddle.
Lindsay solves it.
She gets an advantage
in the immunity challenge.
Turns out, the time advantage
was enough, in theory,
to have won.
But Mike ends up winning,
the guy that some would say,
least likely to win
on a complicated puzzle.
- You said it many times.
- Absolutely.
We get to Tribal Council.
Lindsay can't persuade you
to keep her
because she's too big a threat.
She's now on the jury.
We get to today. Romeo,
a lot of people would have said,
if you're gonna look
at past history,
you're the long shot to win.
And then you win.
And what it reminded me
is that so much of what
we accomplish in life starts
with showing up,
and by showing up,
you're still in the game,
and you have
all the power tonight.
So, as you sit here,
what is that feeling of knowing,
"I hung in there long enough,
and when I needed to,
I did what I had to do"?
I mean, I work with all types
of people back home,
and I encourage them to be
the very best that they can be.
And somehow, in this game,
for the first time,
I had to use that advice
that I give them on myself.
No matter how low I'm feeling,
I still had to keep pushing.
It's just a reminder that
if you just hang on long enough,
it can happen.
And that's why
I was so emotional today
because I did it,
and I'm very proud of myself.
All right, before we get
to your decision,
let me check in
with everybody else. Maryanne,
- how you feeling?
- You know, you always feel like
you're going to vomit
'cause it's like,
I've watched the show and,
like, I've seen people be like,
yeah, they do fire at camp,
and they get here,
and they can't do... They can't
even catch a flame, right?
So, like, even, like, how
confident I feel, it's like
anything can happen
at Tribal, so...
Did you practice making fire?
Yes, I did.
Jonathan, how are you feeling
about your fire-making skills?
I'm pretty good at making fires,
Mr. Jeff.
Mike, what was your take
on the afternoon?
Well, the worst
kept secret at camp was
I'm definitely making fire tonight.
I mean, it's
obviously ironic a bit
that the fireman
would be making fire,
but it doesn't mean
you know how to make them
just because you have
a living of putting them out.
Very true.
I watched Jonathan make fire
for the last 12 to 13 days.
He's very good at it.
I will give it my best shot.
So you feel like it's you and
Jonathan. That's what I heard.
And that's exactly
what I'm saying.
I feel like it's me and Jonathan.
They're putting their best
fire maker against me.
So you're the target?
Absolutely.
All right,
well, let's find out.
So, Romeo, before you tell me,
just walk me through
the different things
you considered and why.
Yeah, I mean, I felt
like Miss Universe,
and this was my crown, and
everybody wanted to talk to me.
It felt great, uh,
but it's not as easy
as-as they think it is.
It was like
a tennis match in my head.
Am I making the right choice?
I don't know.
I might be making a million-
dollar mistake, or not.
I-I don't know, but I've played
my game since day one
based on my gut feeling,
and I'm still here.
So obviously
I did something right.
And, uh, I'm going
with my gut tonight.
Okay. So, congratulations.
First spot at the final three
is yours.
You will get a chance to
plead your case tomorrow night
to this jury.
The next decision is
who's going to be sitting
next to you
in that second spot
at the final three.
Who's that gonna be?
Ah.
I'm taking Maryanne with me.
And these two are making fire.
All right, so, Maryanne,
you are now in the final three.
You, too, will get a chance to plead your case
to the jury tomorrow night.
The only question left
is to see who is going to be
- the third person next to you.
- I love you, brother.
I love you, too, man.
You guys can take your spots.
Good luck, guys.
Give you a minute
to look at everything,
and then we'll begin.
All right, so,
what you're looking to do
is make a flame high enough
and hot enough
to burn through
and raise that flag.
First to do it will be sitting
at the final Tribal Council tomorrow.
The other person will
be sitting on the jury.
Stakes don't get bigger. No.
- Are you both ready?
- Yeah.
- Yes.
Let's begin.
Been doing this since season 35.
Both guys get some coconut husk
and start shaving magnesium.
That magnesium is what's
gonna give you that igniter.
Jonathan,
now trying to get a spark going.
It's one thing to do it at camp,
it's another to do it on
the stage at Tribal Council
with the million dollars
potentially on the line.
No flame yet.
That's pretty normal, too.
Jonathan going back
for sparks again.
Had a little something.
Can he get it? No.
Jonathan once again
trying to nurture
a little spark into a flame.
Can't do it.
Mike still working.
Mike's got flame first.
You only have a limited amount
of coconut husk,
so you don't want
to use all of it.
It burns quickly,
but it also burns out
just as fast.
So once you get a flame,
it's what you do with it.
Mike going for it.
He's putting a lot
of coconut husk up there.
Just dumping sticks on.
Got to keep it going.
Jonathan now has
a little something.
He's working it.
Can he get it to take hold?
Jonathan's got flame now.
He's in it.
He's gonna add
more coconut husk.
Takes a lot
to burn through that rope.
The occasional glance
off of the fibers
of that rope won't be enough.
You got to get a flame that's
gonna be on there for a moment.
Mike's is now
starting to hit the rope
a little more consistently.
It's shooting pretty high.
Jonathan has his going.
Now he's trying
to build something.
Side by side.
25 days into Survivor 42.
A million dollars on the line.
Mike's flame burning high again.
You can see that rope burning
little by little.
Jonathan doing a nice job
to get his fire going.
We've got two good fires
going right now.
Mike adding more sticks.
No real pattern with Mike.
He's just putting timber
on the flame.
Jonathan a little more organized,
trying to build something,
more of a structure.
Mike is more of a backyard, and
he's burning through that rope.
Now the wind is
blowing Mike's flame sideways,
almost into Jonathan.
You're both still in this,
but Mike has
a big fire going right now.
Jonathan has a small fire.
And Mike's flame
is really starting to burn.
It is right where you want it.
It is killing it.
- Yeah! Yes!
- There it is. It's over.
Yes!
Mike will have the final seat
at the final Tribal Council
of Survivor 42.
Oh, my God.
Great matchup.
Both guys got fire. Boom.
The fireman pulled it out.
Mm.
Jonathan, before you pack up,
have a seat.
Yeah.
So what are you thinking,
Jonathan, when you're
looking at your fire?
Which is still going.
That's a decent fire
in the fire-making challenge.
Mike just built an inferno.
Yeah.
You know what, Jeff?
I was thinking when I got here,
if-if I lose,
then I was meant to lose.
I-I gave it what I had.
Mike's just-- he beat me.
Yeah, it's that simple.
Mike, what are you feeling,
because you're the guy
that just took Jonathan out
and earned your spot
in the final three?
You know, it's--
obviously I'm... I-I'm...
ecstatic over
what just happened.
Um, I'm happy that
I went against Jonathan,
because Jonathan
has been known as
the best fire-starter
in the camp.
He's been very, very good at it.
It made it that much more,
um, rewarding for me,
that I went against somebody
that was...
not a pushover.
Jonathan,
you lasted 25 of 26 days.
You got almost
as far as you can go.
It's time to grab your torch.
I love you, brother.
I love you, guys.
And, Mr. Jeff, I got to say.
Say it.
I fought the good fight.
And, Jonathan...
The tribe has spoken.
Time for you to go.
Hey, my friends.
All love.
The same.
Bye, Jon.
All right,
Mike, Romeo, Maryanne.
Regardless how you got here,
you did what 15 other players
in this game could not do.
You made it to the final three.
Your work is not done.
Your last job is to
claim your victory,
and that happens
tomorrow night
when the power shifts
to this jury, plus Jonathan,
who will be there tomorrow.
Tomorrow night they're
gonna put you through a Q and A.
Their job is to hold you
accountable for your actions
and make you prove
why you deserve
the title of Sole Survivor
and the million dollars,
rather than the other two.
This is your last night in Fiji.
I hope you enjoy it.
I hope you get some sleep.
I'll see you tomorrow night
for your final Tribal Council.
- Congratulations.
- Thank you so much. Thank you...
- Thanks, Jeff.
Oh.
I got to tell you,
I was so shocked
to see how fast
my main man Mike
started that fire.
He beat me fair and square.
He earned his spot
in the top three.
And if I get the chance,
you better believe
that I'm gonna be
right back out here.
Thank you, God.
Thank you, Survivor.
Thank you for the opportunity.
Look at the sun.
See it right there,
starting to peek through?
Oh, my God. I love the sun.
Oh, my goodness. That's beautiful.
It's gonna get warm. It's the 26th day.
Oh, my God.
There it is.
Know what's even more beautiful?
Look how different
all three of us are.
- And we're still here.
- I know.
So, it's the morning
of the 26th,
the last day
you're on Survivor.
But, of course, I feel
like this game ain't over.
This game's not over at all.
And immediately
what goes through my head is:
what am I gonna say
to the jury?
How am I gonna talk to the jury?
Eight jury members are gonna
ask hard-hitting questions.
I think I'm sitting
in a good spot,
but does that mean
I'm in a good spot?
If Mike comes out tonight
and says,
"My strategy was
to play a man of integrity
and to stab you in the back,"
fantastic.
Mike played a very good game.
He was able to disarm
and manipulate a lot of people,
Mike, using his social game,
hit the hearts
of a lot of players.
I need Mike to own
that he was a snake.
If that was intentional,
he could get my vote
for a million dollars.
Oh, my God!
Yes! Yes!
Oh!
There's, look, look.
I told you, Danishes.
Oh, my goodness,
Look at... Give me some, brother.
Oh, my God!
Yeah.
If you're voting for the person
that played the best game,
give it to me.
I'm the ultimate underdog.
Cheers for the most unlikely
final three.
And one of us winning a million dollars.
Now we're going
into the final pageant,
and I want that crown
and that Miss Survivor sash.
That's what I want.
Romeo's strength
was the fact that he was weak.
He played the game
on a weaker level,
so he could be forgotten.
And if that was his strategy
and that's the way he played,
that's brilliant, dude.
Romeo's game might deserve
a little bit more
credit and respect,
because basically he said,
"Think of me as a goat."
Take me to the end,
and I'm gonna tell you
exactly why I'm not.
A lot of us want to reward
the most aggressive player,
but why is it
more impressive to be
an elephant than a cockroach,
who's gonna survive
the apocalypse?
I'm truly so full right now.
No. Come on.
I know.
To be successful tonight,
I need to go and be honest
about my game.
At this point,
the roller coaster
has already moved.
There's no getting out,
which means,
when I go down, I have to
raise my hands and scream
and be like,
"This is what I did
in these past 26 days."
I want to show
that I can still be myself
and I can still be weird,
but in the end I can succeed.
People think she was just used
as a vote, as a pawn,
which is why I need Maryanne
to articulate what she did
to drive the season.
I am so happy for Maryanne.
She made herself seem
like this silly, younger girl
who can't be taken seriously,
but I know there's
a lot more to Maryanne
than other people are seeing.
I was with Maryanne
from day one,
and yet I have all this unknown.
You had all this potential
and all this knowledge.
What did you do with it?
I hope Maryanne sways me.
I am a feminist.
I want to give a woman
some money,
but I'm also a competitor
and I can't, in good faith,
just give someone money
because I like them.
I did everything
except for win a challenge,
I believe, on my bucket list.
And we should be proud,
'cause we're the last ones
of our tribe.
Yup.
One Taku, one Vati, one Ika.
Don't ever give up.
You fight and fight and fight.
This is the final fight.
You don't, you don't quit
in the fourth quarter.
I know I can close the deal and
be the winner of Survivor 42.
They're about to be
surprised tonight.
Deep inside this little man,
there's a, uh, a monster.
We did it, guys. Final three.
We did.
Good luck tonight, all right?
My vote
is up for grabs.
I'm hoping
somebody comes with some beef
that deserves
that million dollars.
I can only expect
that the ending of season 42
will be the most
unpredictable ever.
I am making the decision
to change someone's life.
What was your move?
How did you drive the game?
Convince me
why you deserve my vote.
Give me straight-up honesty,
'cause that's
what we're gonna respect.
And I want them to fight.
Fight.
Wow. Here we are.
Final Tribal Council.
Romeo, Maryanne, Mike.
There are stages to Survivor.
You have the beginning, where
you need to form a strong tribe.
Then you have
the individual game.
And then, when
you get down to about five,
you have that final push,
and tonight is the last phase:
claim your victory.
This is it.
You have to convince
this group of people
that you voted out--
you're the reason
they're over there--
you deserve
the title of Sole Survivor
and the million dollars
that goes with it.
If you sit back
and you're passive,
you will not win this game.
Juries have shown this repeatedly.
You got to stand up and take it.
Demand it.
Jury, your job is
to hold them accountable.
Tribal Council has always been
where you are held accountable
for your actions.
You're gonna put them
through an interrogation
that I feel confident
will be tough and respectful.
Both can exist.
All right, I'm gonna give
everybody here a moment.
One big, deep breath,
and then we'll begin.
All right, it's time
for our final
Tribal Council Q and A
from the jury.
We're gonna examine the game tonight
from three different areas:
social, physical, strategic.
And I realize that they often
overlap, and that's okay.
All right. Who wants
to get us started? Omar.
All right.
It's been so long since
we've been able to talk to you,
so I wanted to congratulate
all three of you.
And this season
has been so unpredictable.
And it's so fitting
that you three,
who may be perceived
as three unexpected players,
are the ones that made it here.
And similar to Darwin's theory
of natural selection
and survival of the fittest,
it's not always
the mighty elephant
or the powerful lion
that's gonna win.
Sometimes it's the honeybee,
which causes prosperity
in agriculture
across the world,
or even the cockroach,
who survives this apocalyptic game...
that we've had in season 42.
So, for tonight,
what we really want you
to do is present
your survival of the fittest strategy
and make us sure that
you deserve to win,
because all our votes
are open tonight for any of you.
- So fight for your life tonight.
- That's right.
All right,
let's start with social.
Okay, so, Mike,
my perception of you,
from the outside looking in, is
that you're a man of integrity,
you're a man of honor,
your word means something,
- you really value a handshake.
- Yeah.
It appears that you do not want
to lie or deceive in this game.
Maryanne, my perception of you
is that you're bubbly, young,
you're talkative,
you're silly and goofy.
Sometimes you might
take parts of the game
less seriously than others,
is how it appears.
And, Romeo,
my perception of you is,
there are times when
you are quiet, more reserved,
you know, scattered with bouts
of frantic paranoia
and random votes at Tribal.
So my question, to all of you,
with that perception, is,
is that accurate?
Is that accurate of how you
played the game, who you are?
And if not, what am I missing?
Was there more to it?
- Mike.
- I think it's a great question.
Um, I think you described me
pretty well.
Um, I think I've absolutely
played the game
as honorable
as I could play a game
that is about deception,
about backstabbing.
There was only one time
I went against my word,
and that was to Rocksroy, and
I owe him an apology for that,
but I think
I've played the game true
to how I wanted
to play the game.
Maryanne.
So, I agree with almost
all of your perception with me.
The only part
which I don't agree with
was when you said that I don't
really take the game seriously.
So, me not taking the game seriously
was actually
a part of my strategy.
When I came into the merge, I
realized that there was a trend.
If you were young,
like under 25, and you seemed
like you were strategic,
you would be voted out.
Zach got voted out-- under 25.
Swati got voted out-- under 25.
Lydia got voted out-- under 25.
Tori, you were under 25.
You showed that
you were strategic,
and you were on the bottom
for the whole time.
So I basically had to pretend
that I had no strategy,
and then,
when there were fewer people,
I'd be able
to start to show my strategy
further and further in the game.
Romeo.
So, the only negative word
that you said about me
was, uh, "paranoid."
And, at a certain point, I was,
because, when we got
to the merge of Kula Kula,
I quickly went from
feeling like I was the boss
to the employee.
And I was at the bottom
of every single Tribal Council.
And the random votes,
yes, I did do that,
but that was purposely,
because I didn't want to vote
for the person that was going.
Chanelle, I knew you were going.
I didn't vote for you.
Tori, I'm glad that
I didn't have to vote.
Hai, you saved me,
and I told you I wasn't gonna
vote for you when you went,
and I voted for Jonathan. Um...
But your strategy of throwing
hinky votes to rile people up,
you did that to me,
it succeeded,
and you proceeded
to gaslight me.
So, was that part
of your social game?
No, I did not gaslight you.
You saved me, and
I didn't want to vote for you.
I refused to vote for you.
Let me, let me specify.
The gaslighting was
when I asked you
if you threw the hinky vote
at me at the Chanelle vote-off.
And you said, "No, I did not."
Yes.
So you did gaslight me.
For that time, yes,
because you came at me aggressively.
But you came at me aggressively, too.
I was just-- I let my feelings
get to me.
And it-it came from Drea,
'cause I felt Drea
replaced me with you.
You were so good
that you... that you were...
that she replaced me,
and I'm sorry.
- I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
- Thank you for owning that.
- Thank you.
- I'm sorry.
You admitting that
me getting close to Drea
made you threatened, I respect that.
Yeah. Yeah.
So thank you for being truthful.
Anyone else, social?
Uh, yeah, um, Mike,
you touted a lot around camp
about honesty, integrity,
you're a man of your word.
- Yes.
- And you said earlier, is that the only time
you've ever lied in the game
was to Rocksroy.
But did you not lie to Drea
on the beach
about going after Romeo
to make her feel comfortable?
And you said, "Omar,
we got to vote out Drea.
You know I'm just trying to make her comfortable, right?"
Well, I never purposely
sacrificed my integrity,
but there were times
that I had to do things
that maybe I didn't want to do.
I had to protect myself.
That's honor for myself, also.
Mike, I don't think
I hear you owning up
to what we're asking you. Okay.
And so, I just want to kind of
- really dig in.
- Okay.
How many people in this game
did you shake their hands,
did you look in their eyes,
did you give your word,
and then did
you lie to their faces?
I'm gonna be honest,
there's only one person
that I shook their hand
and said something,
and that was Rocksroy.
Everybody else,
I absolutely kept my word,
and, until, no, no,
until they deceived me first.
And I'll explain what happened.
Rocksroy says to me,
I say to him,
"Is this easy as it is?"
We shook hands.
I said, "I'm voting Romeo."
At the last minute,
you came up to me and said,
"Listen, we have
to vote Rocksroy off."
I said,
"I can't vote Rocksroy off.
I just told him
I wasn't voting him off."
And you said, "No, we have to."
I said, "If we're in an alliance
and I'm your number one,
"how come I didn't know
until 30 minutes prior
to us going to a Tribal?"
You shook my hand,
and you blindsided me.
I was never deceitful. Your words are...
Yes, but then, okay.
So you're telling me
that you weren't deceitful?
- Then-then I...
- I think somebody else might have lied to you.
You don't realize that Omar was
lying to you the entire time?
But then you weren't talking to me.
Yes, I was, Mike.
I didn't even know you were
in an alliance with them.
I told you.
It kind of comes down to,
anybody who's aligned with you
is not allowed
to talk to other people...
- Mm.
- ...when that's how people get information
to be able to give you,
yet you are allowed
to talk to lots of different
people and have one-on-ones.
And that's where
it seems inconsistent.
That's true.
But was that the strategy?
We're trying to understand,
was that strategy,
or was that just like...?
It was.
It was absolutely strategy
to use
my social game for the alliance
I was in and for myself
to advance in the game.
Okay, but you just claimed
that your game was to be honest
and have dignity.
That is not what
it's sounding like, Mike.
- You need to own your game.
- Well... I am, I'm saying it right now.
I just want to,
I just want us to settle down
because we all lied to people.
Mike, I actually think
your social game was on point.
You were very social
with everyone.
And kudos to you,
as a 57-year-old,
staying in the talks
with all of us--
people who are half your age
most of the time.
Thank you. Fortunately my social
game is what I am in real life.
I'm a very social person.
I like people.
I want to know
what makes them tick.
And you guys
opened up your world to me,
introducing me to places, cultures,
religions that I never knew
before, and I just ate it up.
So when I talk to people,
people like me,
and they would just come up
to me and give me information.
I-I respect that,
'cause your social game
is the reason I went home,
straight up.
Like, it saved you.
Thank you.
- I have a question for you, Maryanne.
- Mm-hmm.
At Taku,
I felt that your social game
put you on the bottom.
Did you realize
that your sloppy social game
was putting you in danger,
and did you do anything to
change that later in the game?
Yep. And I can understand that,
and thank you
for pointing it out
and giving me the chance
to explain my social game.
To be completely honest,
I didn't realize that
my social game was as sloppy
as I thought it was
until the fake merge.
I truly was sitting there,
being like, "Wow,
I'm doing such a great job.
I'm living such a great life."
And, like,
I'm gonna be honest about that.
Like, I feel
as if that's because
when I got comfortable,
I started to play
a little bit more emotionally.
When I play emotionally,
I'm someone where I love
to tell everyone everything.
And you literally
can't do that on Survivor.
Does that answer your question?
- Yeah.
- I want to piggyback off of that.
Mm-hmm.
Was there any particular people
that you were
able to draw in yourself
for a vote,
or just for an alliance?
The person who I feel
I specifically went
and drew in for a vote
was Romeo at your vote, Omar,
because Romeo and I were kind of
working back and forth together,
and you two were very gung ho
already about voting Omar out.
- So it was time to take out Omar. But the...
- Hold on.
- That's not... That's not how you knew.
- Yeah.
- I told Mike to team up with you to take Omar out.
This wasn't a move
that you came up with.
Yes, you two did go
and think of it first,
but I can tell you and promise
that I was
already thinking about it.
I was deciding whether
I'd take him out at six or five,
and I will agree that Mike and
you talking to me is what said,
"Okay, it needs to be at six."
Okay.
So I want to hear
the same thing from Romeo.
What is a big social move
that you did, Romeo?
So, for me, I'm more
of a one-on-one conversation,
as opposed to
sitting around camp
and just speaking out loud
in front of groups.
That's not what I do.
Back home,
I work with women one-on-one,
and that's what I did with each
and every one of you,
I felt like, whether I was
in alliance with you or not,
I had a relationship.
So, to answer your question,
that was my social move--
making alliances
with every single person.
- Okay. Got it.
- Like I made with you.
Like I made
with Omar and Maryanne.
Like I made with Drea and Rocks.
Like I made
with every single person.
All right, I'm gonna move this
into the physical part
of the game.
Rocksroy, I can't think of a Survivor in recent memory...
- ...who's enjoyed the physical part of the game as much as you.
- Yeah, buddy.
- Yeah.
- So why don't you get us started in this section?
Uh, one of the things I noticed
is, uh, for a lot of players
this year, is just basic skills.
Doing physical work,
building a shelter,
identifying plants or whatever.
What skills did you guys think
you brought to the game?
Maryanne?
So, one of the things which
I did was weave palm fronds.
So, when we were all still gung
ho about weaving palm fronds,
I showed most of my tribe,
"Hey, this is how we weave it."
And I also used it
for other things.
I made Omar's prayer mat.
This is just an example
to show that
I weave palm fronds.
Another thing
which I knew how to do
was, I was very, very good
at scaling and gutting fish.
My family were-were Luo--
which is a tribe from Kenya--
and we love eating tilapia.
So when you buy it in, like,
little buckets of it,
you have to individually
scale them and gut them.
So I've always been growing up,
watching my mom doing this.
So, even though
I can't catch a fish,
I can go and be like, "Thank you
for bringing this fish.
I'm going to prepare it so
you don't have to do that work."
Mike.
Um, I think
the most important thing,
in regards to strength,
is my work ethic.
I didn't stop moving once
in the 26 days I was out here.
Every single time something
was needed to be done,
even if I didn't know
how to do it. I cut bamboo.
I went and got wood. I built.
You are the only reason
we had a merge shelter.
It was incredible
to watch you work
- the first two weeks of Vati.
- And I got to be honest with you,
I didn't know
what the hell I was doing.
It was fantastic,
and you did it so fast.
- Yeah. It was a nice shelter.
- Yeah.
Thank you. Romeo.
So I'm gonna
be honest with everyone.
I've never been camping
a day in my life.
I just learned how to swim
to come out on Survivor.
I-I was just...
That was very impressive
considering
you just learned how to swim.
I thought you did really, really well.
I was, I was not...
Number one,
I'm terrified of heights.
And I just learned how to swim.
And now I have to do both,
and on national TV,
in my underwear.
So, I'm like...
And you hate hearing Jeff say,
"Romeo dead last."
And-- but-but that last challenge,
I knew I was gonna win.
I didn't care what it was.
I was like,
"I'm not leaving Survivor
without my dream
of wearing that necklace."
And I pulled it through, and I,
and I was so proud of myself.
And I think that was the most
important immunity challenge,
'cause it gave me power.
And it felt good
to have power in this game,
so it meant the world to me.
All right,
let's move into strategy.
So, my vote, just so you know,
is off of game strategy--
how you played this game.
So I want to know
what your biggest move
that you did on your own,
in this game, was.
Um, Romeo.
For me, my game
quickly shifted into,
unfortunately,
a self-preservation game,
'cause my name
was always at the bottom.
I had to make as many alliances
as I could,
and hopefully
that would push me through,
and that did.
But somebody's just gonna say,
"Okay, well,
we'll take Romeo,
'cause we could beat him."
So I figure,
"Okay, I need to do something."
And the first thing was
create a fake immunity idol.
Whether it worked or didn't,
that was just to get people's
attention away from me,
to not vote for me.
Then the last and final
immunity challenge,
I knew I had to win,
to show that nobody carried me
to the final three.
I put myself there.
Why did you take Maryanne
to three?
Mm. Good question.
I felt that she didn't
have a strategy,
and my best move was
to bring somebody that was
perceived
to be playing a similar game.
And I secured my own fate
by putting myself
in the final three, and-and...
and the rest is up to you guys.
Mike, what's something that
you solely did on your own?
Once we got to the merge,
I decided to make my big move.
And I thought
Hai was too strong.
I was nervous
that he was coming at me.
And I organized
a blindside on Hai.
And that's when
I started working
with, uh, Lindsay and Omar
to better my game strategically.
Do you think you played
an emotionally-charged game,
or do you think
you played a strategic game?
I think I played both.
I think I played
a strategic game,
but I also think I played
an emotional game, too.
Sometimes my emotion
got the best of me.
Um...
- I'm-
- I'm being told that I gave my word,
and I, and I went
against it a lot.
Well, if I'm being honest
with you,
maybe I didn't play as much
with integrity as I thought
I did, to be honest with you.
And I, maybe I misconstrued
exactly what I was doing.
But again, you have to say
some stuff that is not true,
or else you're
gonna get steamrolled.
You're gonna be voted out.
I would have
been out a long time ago
if I didn't do what I did--
I know I would have.
So at seven on, I realized I'm
playing the game of Survivor.
I used the beginning
of the game to set up that game,
and then, from seven down,
I played the game
that I thought that would
best get me to the end.
Maryanne, I'm really,
really interested
in what you have to say,
'cause we slept together
by the fire every night,
and I don't know what
you really did in the game.
My one big move
that I did was set myself up
to be in the final three,
with multiple combinations
with Omar's vote.
Let me explain to you why.
When I voted out Omar,
Mike gave me his word
that he will give me
his idol at the final five,
and that would
guarantee me the final four.
But then, you know,
you might be like,
"Mike backed on his word.
So, like, how were you so sure?"
And the reason is, I kept
the only secret in this game.
I, actually, after your vote,
Tori, had the merge idol.
I can show it to you right now.
And I told no one about it.
You can see it over here.
Here's the idol.
Here's the note.
So now we're then
off to my final four
of Jonathan, Mike, me and Romeo.
So that meant that if I won,
I'm going to the end,
because I'm not making fire.
If Mike won, he gave me his word
that I would go to the end.
If Romeo won,
Romeo was afraid of Mike,
he would take me to the end.
And if Jonathan won,
he would want to go
and have that final big move
to take Mike out,
and Romeo and I
would be at the end.
By taking you out, Omar,
I gave myself the best position
to be sitting here.
Touché.
I have a question.
What's your story
of your personal evolution
playing this game?
Like, what did you learn
about yourself?
Romeo, I'd like you to start.
Um, I felt like,
for at least
the second part of this game,
I was holding on
by the skin of my teeth.
And back home I would say,
"Screw it. Let me just
try something else."
But out here,
I couldn't do that
because I was not just
representing me.
That was not the game
I wanted to play.
I didn't want to play
from the bottom,
but that was the game
that was dealt to me.
And I-I-I... and I saw
an opening and a window
for these two people
that were going to play with me.
And then, the next vote,
these three people want
to play with me.
And then this person was gone,
so then
I had to find another person,
and I just kept going
until I won that final immunity,
and that's what I'm going
to take away from this game,
is, no matter
how hard this game was--
and I can tell this
to the girls
that I work with,
empowering back home--
I didn't give up.
I'm leaving this game
as a free man
who will no longer have to hide
because I'm scared
of what people might think--
even my religious family
back home--
just because I'm gay,
and they won't accept me.
I'm going to... I'm going
to leave this game as a free man
to live my life the way I wanted
to live since I was 19.
And it took me
in my 30s to figure it out.
And just a quick shout-out
to you
for making me comfortable
to do that.
Thank you.
Thank you. Mike?
So, for me, I think
that I proved that
people that are older,
like myself
and Rocksroy, can come out here,
compete in the game,
play the game hard,
and get along
with the younger generation,
which sometimes is not so easy.
For myself, I-I learned that
I can still do what I thought
I couldn't do anymore.
You know, I-I-I talked a lot
about my kids, and it just...
For my kids
to see me come out here
and do what I did
and... and-and compete
and-and... and succeed
to a certain level,
that they would see
that they can do anything
that they've put their mind
to it,
and that there was no...
There's no boundaries
as to what they can accomplish
in their life.
So that's what I learned
about myself.
Maryanne?
So,
the thing which I really learned
about myself is that,
a lot of times we talk about
how Survivor breaks you down,
how it takes your insecurities.
And I realized, I,
with the Omar vote,
made my path to the end.
But there was a chance that
I was going to lose the game
and not know why.
So then I started
to self-sabotage myself.
I really wanted
to bring Lindsay to the end,
but in my mind, I'm like,
"I cannot beat Lindsay."
'Cause that means
that I wanted to go
and give myself an easy out
because I didn't want
to feel that rejection
of friendship.
Even recently in my life,
a couple years ago,
someone spread a rumor about me,
and I lost so many friends,
and I didn't want
to feel that again.
I kind of knew
that that's how I self-sabotage.
Like, when I was young,
I used to push people away
so they couldn't go
and hurt me first.
And it's like,
to know that I'd do it
in something that I love, too,
it's like, it shows
that I still need
to grow as a person,
and I'm still growing,
which is why, like,
I'm still proud of myself.
Because I really,
really was so, so close
to playing my idol for you,
like, before we went to Tribal.
But I'm like, "Maryanne,
you need to grow and you need
to make yourself open." Like,
I knew that I still had
to take that chance to lose
because I deserve
that chance to win.
Thank you.
Thank you for your transparency.
Jury, I have to say,
one of the best
final Tribals
that I can remember.
You held them accountable, but
you were always respectful
and at times
even encouraging
and inspiring them
to try to give a better answer.
And, Romeo, Maryanne and Mike,
you did a great job.
It's very hard to sit over there
and take that from them,
- but that is what you want.
- Very hard.
You want the opportunity
for them to grill you,
and I think all three of you
held yourself in really
high regard. You should be
very proud of yourselves.
- We're going to take a moment.
- Thank you guys.
We're going
to let the jury take in
everything they've just heard.
And when we come back,
we will vote
for a winner of Survivor 42.
- And congratulations, guys.
- Congratulations.
- Yes.
Thanks.
You guys roasted me good.
Probst: ALL RIGHT FOR THE
LAST TIME IN SURVIVOR 42 IS IS
TIME TO VOTE, CHANELLE, YOU'RE
UP.
Probst: I'LL GO GET THE
VOTES.
WELL, THERE IS NO SUCH THING AS
BE EASY SEASON OF SURVIVOR.
THERE'S NOT AN EASY DAY OF
SURVIVOR.
YOU COULD ARGUE THERE IS NOT AN
EASY MINUTE OF SURVIVOR.
YOU ARE STRIPPED OF EVERYTHING.
DROPPED IN A JUNGLE WITH A BUNCH
OF PEOPLE WHO WANT TO TAKE YOU
OUT.
AND YOU DID IT.
YOU MADE IT TO THE FINAL THREE.
NOW ALL YOU WANT TO KNOW IS WHO
WON.
THERE IS ONE MORE TWIST THIS
SEASON.
STOP IT.
OH WOW.
Probst: BECAUSE WE SHOOT
OUR SEASONS BACK TO BACK YOU
DON'T KNOW ANYTHING THAT
HAPPENED IN SURVIVOR 41.
AND WHAT WE DID IN SURVIVOR 41
WAS WE READ THE VOTES IN THE
JUNGLE OF FIJI AND THAT'S WHAT
WE ARE GOING TO DO RIGHT NOW.
NO!
Probst: WE'RE GOING TO READ
THESE VOTES.
WE'RE GOING TO FIND THE WINNER
OF SURVIVOR 42.
ARE WE READY?
YEAH!
GOOD LUCK.
YES.
OH MY GOD.
Probst: HERE WE GO.
FIRST VOTE, MIKE.
MARIANNE, ONE VOTE MARYANNE, ONE
VOTE MIKE.
MARYANNE.
TWO VOTES MARYANNE, ONE VOTE
MIKE.
MARYANNE, THREE VOTES MARYANNE,
ONE VOTE MIKE.
MARIANNE, THAT'S FOUR VOTES
MARYANNE, ONE VOTE MIKE.
THE WINNER OF SURVIVOR 42,
MARIANNE, WITH FIVE, THAT'S
ENOUGH.
CHEESIER CHEESIER.
Probst: COME ON OVER, JURY,
COME ON OVER.
WHAT ELSE THEY DON'T KNOW IS
WE'RE GOING TO BE DOING A
SURVIVOR AFTER SHOW WITH
EVERYBODY RIGHT NOW.
WHICH WE ALSO DID LAST SEASON.
BRING OUT THE CHAMPAGNE.
BRING IN THE SIGNS.
LET'S BRING IT ALL IN.
THIS IS THE BEST PART.
THE SURPRISE OF SHOOTING BACK TO
BACK SEASONS THEY DIDN'T KNOW
EVERYTHING WAS GOING TO HAPPEN.
WE WILL BRING A COUPLE CAMERAS
AROUND, BRING IN MORE FIRE.
WHEN WE COME BACK WE WILL HAVE
EVERYBODY HERE AND WHEN THEY ARE
STILL IN THIS GREAT RAW ENERGY,
I WILL TAKE SOME CHAMPAGNE RIGHT HERE.
SURVIVOR 42 AFTER PARTY COMING
UP AFTER THIS.
Probst: ALL RIGHT, SO WE
ARE STILL IN THE JUNGLES OF
FIJI.
WE'VE JUST CROWNED OUR WINNER,
23 YEAR OLD MARYANNE WHO JUST
WON SURVIVOR 42.
ONE OF THE YOUNGER WINNERS IN
OUR 42 SEASONS.
LET'S START WITH YOU.
WHAT IS THIS FEELING RIGHT NOW?
BECAUSE ONE OF THE THINGS I WANT
TO ASK THE JURY, I THINK THEY
CAME IN UNDECIDED.
I THINK YOU SWAYED THEM TONIGHT.
DID YOU FEEL THAT HAPPENING?
AT FIRST I FELT AS IF I
WASN'T BEING ASKED QUESTIONS AND
THAT WAS DEMORALIZING BECAUSE
OH, THEY EITHER KNOW MY STORY
AND THAT SAY GOOD THING OR THEY
DON'T WANT TO KNOW MY STORY AND
THAT IS A GOOD THING BUT
HONESTLY I KNEW THE PIVOTAL
MOMENTS WAS TELL BEING THE IDOL
AND HOW I SET MYSELF IN THE END,
I KNEW COMPARED TO OTHER PEOPLE
ON THE JURY I DIDN'T REALLY PLAN
A BIG STRATEGIC GAME, I WILL TO
PROVE I WAS HERE TO PLAY, NOT
JUST TO GET TO THE END.
I WANTED-- TO BE THE 40th
WINNER OF THE SHOW IS, LIKE I
STILL CAN'T BELIEVE THIS IS HAPPENING.
Probst: CLARIFYING BECAUSE
TWO PEOPLE HAVE WON TWICE.
YES, SORRY.
Probst: SHOW OF HANDS, WHO
HERE CAME IN UNDECIDED?
OKAY, SO VIRTUALLY EVERYBODY.
WHEN HAI WHEN YOU SAY UNDECIDED
WERE YOU SWAYED BY MARYANNEOR
LEANING ONE WAY THE OTHER.
I DON'T WANT MY SHIRT TO
THROW YOU OFF.
I WAS UNDECIDED MOSTLY BECAUSE
WE DIDN'T WORKING TO FOR A LARGE
PART OF THE GAME.
AND WE ALL CAME IN WANTING TO
KNOW YOUR STRATEGY.
BECAUSE IT WAS PRETTY ELUSIVE TO
A LOT OF US.
SAME WITH ROMEO.
I THINK MIKE WAS A LITTLE MORE
VISIBLE.
BUT FOR US WE WANTED TO GIVE YOU
AN OPPORTUNITY TO EXPLAIN YOURSELF.
AND YOU DID IT SO ELOQUENTLY.
Probst: SO DREA WITH SO
MANY PEOPLE COMING IN UNDECIDED,
WHAT DO YOU THINK HAPPENED?
BECAUSE IT WAS A 7-1 VOTE, THE
OTHER TWO VOTES WERE MARY ANN'S
AS WELL.
RIGHT, I THINK, AND I KNOW IT
CAME OFF AS IF I WAS COMING OFF HARSH.
BUT WE KNEW THAT MIKE HAD BEEN
PLAYING THE GAME SINCE DAY ONE.
SO I REALLY WANTED TO GIVE HER
THE HARD QUESTIONS SO SHE COULD
EXPLAIN HERSELF IN DETAIL.
Probst: WAS THERE ANYBODY
WHO WAS LEANING TOWARD MIKE THAT
GOT SWAYED BY MARYANNE?
ME.
Probst: REALLY?
SO ROCKSROY, TORI, LINDSAY, A
LITTLE BIT OMAR AND WERE ALL
LEANING MIKE.
WAS IT THAT MIKE FALTERED AT THE
END OR MARYANNE STEPPED UP.
FOR ME IT WAS TWO FACTORS.
ONE IS THAT MIKE PLAYED A MORE
OBVIOUSLY STRATEGIC GAME.
AND YOU KNOW WHAT, I WAS REALLY
LIKING FOR MIKE WAS YEAH, I
PLAYED THE HONOR, I PLAYED THE
INTEGRITIES CARD BUT I WAS
PLAYING TO WIN THE WHOLE TIME.
AND I DIDN'T FEEL LIKE I GOT
THAT.
WHEREAS MARYANNE I WAS REALLY
TIGHT WITH HER FROM THE START,
HER STRATEGIC MIND WAS BRILLIANT
BUT I NEVER SAW THE EXECUTION
UNTIL SHE PULLED OUT THAT I HAD
A BACKUP PLAN AT FINAL FIVE AND
THAT IDOL THAT EVERYBODY IS
ELUSIVELY LOOKING FOR, SHE HAD
IT FOR AWHILE.
SO THAT REALLY CINCHED THE DEAL
FOR ME.
IT WAS A COMBINATION OF MIKE
LOSING IT AND MARYANNE SNATCHING
IT RIGHT AT THE VERY END.
Probst: MIKE, LET'S TALK
ABOUT THIS.
YOU JUST HEARD THEM SAY THAT A
LOT OF PEOPLE CAME IN HERE,
LEANING TOWARD YOU.
AND THEN MARYANNE STEPPED UP AND
TOOK T EVEN THOUGH YOU DIDN'T
WIN.
YOU FOUND AN IDOL.
YOU WON AN IMMUNITY CHALLENGE.
YOU WON THE FIRE-MAKING, YOU HIT
ALMOST ALL OF THE BIG ICONIC
MOMENTS IN SURVIVOR.
SO WHAT IS THAT FEELING RIGHT
NOW FOR YOU, EVEN AS A
RUNNER-UP?
SO IT IS IN BETWEENMENT I
PLAYED SURVIVOR, I PLAYED THE
HARDEST CAN I PLAY, I HAVE NO
REGRETS AND AFTER HEARING
MARYANNE'S STORY TONIGHT, I
THINK SHE EARNED IT.
THERE IS ABSOLUTELY NO
ANIMOSITY.
I AM GOOD, I PLAYED SURVIVOR AT
THE AGE OF 57 AFTER WATCHING IN
21 YEARS, I DID A LOT OF THINGS
THAT HONESTLY THAT I WATCHED ON
TV, I CAN'T BELIEVE IT.
SO IT'S A GREAT DAY FOR ME TOO,
IT IS.
Probst: AND ROMEO, ST
ALWAYS HARD WHEN SOMEBODY MAKES
IT THIS DEEP AND DOESN'T GET ANY VOTES.
WHAT IS THE FEELING YOU HAVE?
BECAUSE I FELT LIKE YOU MOVED A
LOT OF PEOPLE TONIGHT.
AND PROBABLY GOT CLOSER TO THEIR
VOTE THAN YOU WERE WHEN YOU
WALKED IN.
AND I'M SEEING A LOT OF PEOPLE
NODDING RIGHT NOW, DID YOU FEEL
THAT AS WELL.
COULD YOU FEEL THAT YOU WERE
MOVING THEM?
YEAH, BUT YOU KNOW, JEFF, FOR
ME I DIDN'T COME HERE FOR A
MILLION DOLLARS.
I CAME HERE TO SEE IF I COULD
OUT, YOU KNOW, MAKE IT TO THE
END OF SURVIVOR.
AND I DID THAT.
AND I'M LEAVING THIS GAME WITH
LIFE EXPERIENCES THAT I WOULD
HAVE NEVER GOTTEN IF I HADN'T
BEEN HERE.
SO I HAVE NO REGRETS.
AND TO ME BEING ABLE TO LEAVE
THE JUNGLES OF FIJI AND BE FREE
AND LIVE THE LIFE THAT I WANTED
TO LIVE FOR A LONG TIME MEANS
MORE TO ME THAN WINNING A
MILLION DOLLARS.
SO I FEEL LIKE I'M LEAVING HERE
A WINNER.
Probst: ALL RIGHT, I HAVE A
LOT MORE TO TALK ABOUT.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A QUICK
BREAK, ANYBODY THAT NEEDS TO GET
A REFILL ON CHAMPAGNE, LET'S
LOAD IT UP.
WE'LL BRING IN MORE PIZZA AND
CONTINUE WITH THE SURVIVOR 42 AFTERSHOW.
MIKE, YOU'RE STARVING, ART YOU.
LET'S BRING IN A BUNCH OF PIES,
JUST FOR MIKE.
UP NEXT, PLAYERS RECOUNT SOME OF
THE BEST MOMENTS OF THE SEASON.
PLUS LATER, YOUR FIRST LOOK AT
SURVIVOR 43.
Probst: WELCOME BACK TO THE
SURVIVOR 42 AFTER SHOW WHERE
PIZZAS ARE BEING DELIVERED,
CHAMPAGNE IS BEING DRUNK.
I WANT TO TALK ABOUT SOME GAME MOMENTS.
LINDSAY, DREA AND HAI, STRAIGHT
OUT OF THE GATE, DOES EVERYBODY
KNOW WHAT HAPPENED IN THE
OPENING CHALLENGE.
STOP, YOU MUST WAIT FOR ALL
THREE PLAYERS BEFORE YOU MAKE
THE DECISION.
GOOD NEWS IT REQUIRES EFFORT
FROM YOU.
IF YOU WANT YOU CAN GRAB YOUR
PADDLES AND RACE BACK TO YOUR
TRIBE OR YOU CAN AGREE TO
SECRETLY WORK TOGETHER AND EACH
EARN AN ADVANTAGE IN THE
PROCESS.
Probst: LING SAI, IS THE
FASTEST THE THREE OF YOU DID
THAT A SIGN OF HOW YOU HAVE TO
PLAY SURVIVOR IN THAT IT WAS ONE
MINUTE INTO DAY ONE AND YOU HAD
ALREADY MADE YOUR DECISION TO GO
FOR IT.
YEAH, I MEAN THEY BOTH
PERSUADED ME INTO SAYING YES.
BECAUSE I KIND OF SAID NO.
AND THEN I READ IT AND I'M LIKE
WELL THIS IS DEFINITELY WORSE
THAN GOOD.
SO I HAVE TO HOPE THAT THEY
DON'T BELOW UP THEIR OWN GAME
AND BELOW UP MY GAME.
AND IT ENDED UP WORKING OUT
GREAT.
WHERE NONE OF US WANTED TO GO
AFTER EACH OTHER.
WE ACTUALLY ALL WANTED TO WORK
TOGETHER.
AND IT WAS JUST LIKE WEIRD.
BUT AWESOME.
AND I THINK THAT JUST KIND OF
SAYS SOMETHING ABOUT ALL OF US.
I DON'T KNOW, THERE WAS A HUGE
RESPECT LEVEL THAT WAS DIFFERENT
THAN JUST SAVAGERY, SOLO GAME
PLAN.
AND I THOUGHT THAT WAS A BIG
TWIST THAT I WASN'T EXPECTING
WHEN I FIRST OPENED THAT
ADVANTAGE.
Probst: AND AGAIN I KEEP
FEELING LIKE I HAVE TO SAY THIS.
WE HAVE NOT SEEN ANY OF SEASON
41 OURSELVES AS PRODUCERS.
WE ARE SHOOTING BACK TO BACK.
I HAVE BEEN IN THE JUNGLE SO
LONG I HAVE A MULLETTE.
NOBODY HAS SEEN ANYTHING BUT
THERE HAVE BEEN THEMES IN BOTH.
AND ONE WAS FUN.
WE FELT LIKE COMING OUT OF THE
YEAR WE HAD, WE WANTED TO HAVE FUN.
AND WITH THE BLOOD AND THE MUD,
YOU CAME BACK LOOKING LIKE YOU
HAD BEEN IN A WAR.
I WAS LIKE WE'RE GOING TO
COMMIT TO, THIS AND HAI WAS
LIKE-- AND OPEN YOUR-- HIGH,
PUTTING THE MUD OVER HIM,
ROLLING IN SAND.
I THOUGHT IF WE ARE GOING TO
PLAY THIS GAME WE'RE GOING TO
GIVE IT ALL WE GOT.
AND OBVIOUSLY I'M GETTING THE
ADVANTAGE SO WE KIND OF-- .
Probst: DREA LET'S TALK
ABOUT ADVANTAGES.
BECAUSE I DON'T KNOW, I DIDN'T
CHECK THE RECORDS BUT I'M NOT
SURE HOW MANY PEOPLE HAVE HAD AS
MANY ADVANTAGES AT ONE TIME AS
YOU DID.
WALK ME THROUGH THE LIST OF WHAT
YOU HAD AT YOUR HEIGHT A AND
WHAT THAT FELT LIKE.
I HAD AN IDOL.
I HAD AN EXTRA VOTES.
I HAD MY SHOT IN THE DARK.
AND THEN I HAD MY KNOWLEDGE
TOWER ADVANTAGE AS WELL.
AND MY AM YOU LET.
SO I STRATEGICALLY PUT ALL MY
ADVANTAGES IN MY LEFT STOCK AND
TIED IT UP THREE TIMES AND PUT
THAT SOCK IN MY LEFT LEG OF MY
BLUE TIGHTS AND TIED THAT UP
FOUR TIMES.
THAT'S IMPRESSIVE.
SO LIKE I KNEW IF SOMEONE WENT
THROUGH MY BAG.
Probst: GENERAL QUESTION IS
THERE ANYONE HERE THAT WILL
ADMIT WHEN THE FIRST FUNNY
PHRASE WAS SAID WHICH IS
MARYANNE TALKING ABOUT THE BUNNY
RABBIT IN THE MAIL BOX, THAT YOU
DIDN'T PICK UP ON IT.
YOU JUST THOUGHT SHE WAS-- OKAY,
IS THERE ANYONE WHO HEARD ALL
THREE PHRASES AND STILL DID NOT
KNOW.
GOOD.
I THINK I WASN'T PAYING
ATTENTION, JEFF, REALLY.
I THINK AFTER THE SECOND TIME
MARYANNE SAID THE PHRASE, I KIND
OF LIKE TUNED OUT.
I WAS LIKE OKAY, I'M FOCUSING ON
WHAT THE CHALLENGE IS GOES TO BE.
HAVE I TO DIVE OFF OF WHAT, HOW
HIGH UP.
I WAS NOT, I WAS NOT FOCUSED ANY MORE.
SO I GUESS RIGHT OVER MY HEAD.
Probst: DO OR DIE, LINDSAY,
ONE OF MY FAVORITE NEW TWISTS
BECAUSE IT IS LITERALLY DO OR
DIE.
IT SEEMED LIKE YOU KIND OF
ENJOYED IT EVEN THOUGH IT HAD TO
BE PETRI FYING.
YEAH, I MEAN IT WAS AWESOME.
LIKE IT WAS REALLY COOL.
AND SAYING THE COOLEST PART
ABOUT T THE ADRENALINE RUSH AND
EXCITEMENT AND THRILL AND WORRY
AND THAT FEAR WAS REALLY COOL.
Probst: AND WOULD YOU HAVE
BEEN OKAY IF YOU HAD DIED.
WITH THE TWIST, YES.
THE GAMBLE THAT I MADE, NO.
SO I STILL WAS VERY REGRETFUL OF
MAKING THAT GAMBLE DECISION.
BUT THE DO OR DIE ITSELF IS A
COOL TWIST THAT YOU HAVE TO
ACCEPT, IF YOU DON'T PICK THE
RIGHT BOX LIKE BEING OKAY WITH
IT, THAT IS WHAT I WOULD HAVE
REGRETTED, NOT NECESSARILY JUST
THE DO OR DIE CHANCE THING.
Probst: I ALSO HAVE TO
POINT OUT, YOU WERE LODGELY
SLATED TO BE IN SURVIVOR 41.
YOU TESTED POSITIVE FOR COVID,
COULD NOT COME OUT.
AND I REMEMBER WHEN WE TALKED ON
THE SHOWN AND I WAS SO SAD FOR
YOU, AND I HUNG UP AND I SAID
WOW, HER ATTITUDE IS AMAZING
BECAUSE YOU SAID HEY, YOU KNOW T
WILL HAPPEN.
SORRY, YOU EVEN SAID ON THE
PHONE WHEN I WAS LIKE YOU NEVER
KNOW WHAT IS GOING TO HAPPEN.
ARE YOU TALKING ABOUT SEASON
43, RIGHT, AND I WAS LIKE NO,
I'M TALKING ABOUT SEASON 42.
IF IT HAPPENS TO SOMEBODY ELSE,
I MIGHT BE ON 42.
AND I HUNG UP AND I WENT
SHE'S PRETTY OPTIMISTIC.
Probst: ALL RIGHT, WE WILL
TAKE ANOTHER QUICK BREAK, WHEN
WE COME BACK MORE FROM FIJI, THE
SURVIVOR SEASON 42 AFTER SHOW.
MIKE, MORE PIZZA.
YEAH.
Probst: UP NEXT, PLAYERS
SHARE THEIR THOUGHTS ON THE NEW
ERA OF SURVIVOR AND HOW
DIFFICULT IT IS TO MANAGE
EMOTIONS IN THE GAME.
Probst: I LOVE ARE YOU
HAVING SO MUCH PIZZA SO MUCH
CHAMPAGNE, LET'S JUST KEEP TALKING.
I WANT TO TALK ABOUT THE WHOLE
NEW ERA OF SURVIVOR WHICH IS THE
26 DAY NO RICE, VERY TOUGH, YOU
EARN EVERYTHING, CRAZY TWISTS,
MORE DANGEROUS GAME.
CHANELLE, LET'S START WITH YOU.
HOW BIG AN IMPACT IS THE NO
RICE?
MAN, I MEAN IF SOMEONE TOLD
ME THAT I WOULDN'T EAT FOR 11
DAYS, I WOULD BE LIKE YOU'RE
CRAZY, THE WAY THAT YOU
PHYSICALLY FEEL.
I REMEMBER STANDING UP AND JUST
BEING DIZZY AND SEEING STARS AND
NOT BEING ABLE TO WALK MORE THAN
THREE STEPS WITHOUT BEING WINDED.
AND SO IT REALLY IMPACTS YOUR
BODY AND IT MAKES THE GAME THAT
MUCH HARDER.
Probst: JONATHAN, ANOTHER
PART OF THIS GAME THAT WE DIDN'T
TALK ABOUT BUT BECAME VERY
EVIDENT AS YOU WERE PLAYING IT,
IT IS RARE AT TRIBAL THAT THERE
ARE MORE THAN SIX OR SEVEN PEOPLE.
WE BROKE YOU UP INTO DIFFERENT GROUPS.
TALK ABOUT THE IMPACT OF THAT.
WHEN YOU START WITH A SMALL
TRIBE AND YOU DON'T HAVE
ANYWHERE TO HIDE AT TRIBAL.
WELL, BEING A BIGGER GUY, I
ALREADY FELT LIKE COMING INTO
THIS THAT I COULDN'T HIDE ANYWAYS.
AND NOW THAT WE HAVE SMALL
TRIBES, I WAS THINKING WELL NOW
THERE'S DEFINITELY NO PLACE TO HIDE.
AND THE ODDS OF ME GETTING
KICKED OUT ARE MORE THAN EVER.
AND THAT WORRIED ME, MR. JEFF,
THAT I COULD BE ONE OF THE FIRST
TO GET KICKED OFF.
AND IT SCARED ME TO DEATH.
Probst: AND OMAR, ON TOP OF
IT, NOT EVERYBODY KNEW EARLY ON
THAT WHEN YOU TOOK THESE
JOURNEYS YOU HAD OPPORTUNITIES
TO GET SOMETHING.
BUT IT REQUIRED YOU TO RISK
LOSING YOUR VOTE.
YEAH, AND ON TOP OF THAT THE
SHOT IN THE DARK MIGHT TAKE
VOTES AWAY.
SO YOU ARE IN A SITUATION,
ESPECIALLY WHEN THE NUMBERS ARE
SO SMALL WHERE YOU MAY THINK
SOMETHING'S HAPPENING AND
SOMETHING COMPLETELY, A SECOND,
THIRD OR EVEN FOURTH TARGET
COULD GO HOME THAT WAS NEVER
SUPPOSED TO GO HOME IN THE FIRST
PLACE.
YOU HAVE TO ALWAYS BE THINKING
AND ANTICIPATING WHAT OTHER
PEOPLE ARE DOING MORE THAN EVER
BEFORE.
MIKE, EVEN THE BEWARE
ADVANTAGES, THEY SAY VERY
CLEARLY BEWARE.
DO YOU GET EXCITED WITH THOSE
KINDS OF CHANGES WHERE IT IS
RISKIER.
THIS GAME IS MORE DIFFICULT NOW
THAN IT WAS?
IT IS EXTREMELY RISKY.
WHEN I FOUND MY IDOL I SAID
BEWARE, IMMEDIATELY I GRABBED T
I DON'T CARE WHAT THE BEWARE IS,
THE THRILL OF EVEN FINDING IT
BUT THEN WHEN YOU OPEN IT UP
REALITY HITS AND YOU SAY OH
CRAP, I DON'T WANT THIS.
ST ALMOST LIKE WHOA, GET BACK.
BUT THEN YOU HAVE TO THINK ABOUT
DID AND SAY LIKE IF YOU HAVE AN
ADVANTAGE THAT TELLS YOU YOU
LOSE YOUR VOTE, YOU KIND OF HAVE
TO TELL SOMEBODY.
BECAUSE IF YOU HAVE TO SPLIT
VOTES OR SOMETHING, YOU KNOW YOU
ARE GOING TO BE EXPOSED ANYWAY.
WHICH HAPPENED AT OUR VOTES.
YOU HAVE ANOTHER SURVIVOR
FIRST, THERE WERE ONLY TWO VOTES
CAST WHICH MEANS TWO PEOPLE DID
NOT VOTE.
DIDN'T ANTICIPATE HAVING TO
REVEAL WHO YOU ARE, BUT NOW
BECAUSE OF A TIE AND THE
INABILITY TO VOTE SOMEBODY OUT,
YOU HAVE TO.
SO WHO DIDN'T VOTE.
WE WILL TO RAISE OUR HAND LIKE
THIS, LIKE WE GOT CAUGHT, WE
DON'T HAVE OUR VOTE.
Probst: HOW ABOUT YOU
LINDSAY, OVERALL APPROACH TO THE
GAINL, OF SURVIVOR, DID IT FEEL
RISKIER OR MORE DANGEROUS,
BECAUSE YOU COME IN BLIND, YOU
DON'T KNOW WHAT IS IN STORE FOR
YOU, BUT WE HAD CONSCIENCELY
DECIDED WITH 41 AND 42 TO MAKE
IT MORE FUN AND MORE DANGEROUS
AND SEE WHERE IT TAKES US.
I ACTUALLY LOVED IT.
AT THE BEGINNING IT WAS KIND OF
DIFFICULT, LIKE WHEN YOU ARE
REALLY LIVING IT AND ALL THESE
THINGS ARE HAPPENING AND YOU
LIKE THIS SUK SUCKS, THIS SUCKS,
THIS SUCKS ALL HARD DIFFICULT
THINGS BECAUSE WE ALL WATCHED
ALL OF THE SEASONS SO AT THIS
POINT THINGS ARE MORE
PREDICTABLE.
WE ARE ALREADY LIKE MENTALLY
PLANNING WHAT THE THINGS ARE
GOING TO BE NEXT AND WITH ALL OF
THESE TWISTS YOU ARE LIKE I
DIDN'T KNOW THIS WAS GOING TO
HAPPEN.
BUT THEN I WAS LIKE HALFWAY
THROUGH, THIS IS PRETTY AWESOME
BECAUSE WE ARE ALL KIND OF
EXPERIENCING A WHOLE NEW GAME
THAT NO ONE IS AWARE OF RATHER
THAN PLAYING A GAME THAT EVERY
ONE KNOWS EVERYONE'S MOVE AND
WHAT IS GOING TO HAPPEN.
I WAS LIKE THIS IS PRETTY COOL.
IT'S LIKE ARE YOU IN A GAME OF
JUMANJI BECAUSE ARE YOU LIVE,
BUT YOU HAVE NO IDEA WHAT THE
TWISTS ARE.
BUT IT IS COOL TO TAKE THE RIDE,
I LOVED IT.
Probst: LET'S TALK ABOUT
MANAGING EMOTIONS IN THE GAME.
MARYANNE.
I WASN'T COMING TO YOU BECAUSE
YOU ARE EMOTIONAL.
BASE YOUR EMOTIONS ARE ACTUALLY,
TO ME WERE ALWAYS JUST REALLY
FUN AND OPENING.
YOU WERE VERY ACCEPTABLE.
BUT LET'S START WITH YOU.
HOW DO YOU FEEL WITH THE
EMOTIONS?
WHAT DID YOU LEARN ABOUT
YOURSELF AND YOUR ABILITY IN THE
MOMENTS TO MANAGE YOUR EMOTIONS.
I FEEL THAT IT IS A REALLY
BIG THING WHICH I LEARNED,
ESPECIALLY THE HIGHS AND LOWS OF
SURVIVOR THAT YOU NEED TO
VALIDATE YOUR FEELINGS, YOU
KNOW.
A LOT OF TIMES WHEN IT IS
RAINING AND YOU FEEL MISERABLE
YOU ARE LIKE SO MANY PEOPLE WANT
TO DO THIS AND I FEEL BAD THAT
I'M FEELS BAD.
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT, ST OKAY THAT
THIS IS A PART OF THE EXPERIENCE.
I'M GOING TO MOVE.
LIKE I'M GOING TO BE ABLE TO GO
TO THE NEXT THING LIKE I
SURVIVED THIS.
BUT RIGHT NOW I DON'T WANT TO
SIR VIVE THIS.
I WANT TO BE HOME AND WARM AND I
DON'T WANT TO BE HERE.
AND THAT'S OKAY BECAUSE WE ALL
HAVE OUR LOWS AND OUR HIGHS.
TORI, I REMEMBER A FEW TIMES
AT TRIBAL WONDERING WHAT YOU
WERE DOING BECAUSE YOU WOULD
TAKE HEAT, AND SO YOUR CREDIT
YOU WOULD TURN AND PUSHBACK.
DID YOU EVER GO BACK TO CAMP AND
HAVE YOUR OWN INTERNAL MONOLOGUE
ABOUT HOW YOU WERE FEELING
ABSOLUTELY.
I TRIED MORE-- CRIED MORE THAN I
THOUGHT I WOULD, AND IT IS FUNNY
BECAUSE MY FAMILY, HAVE I SO
MANY FAMILY MEMBERS BECAUSE THEY
SAID THEIR BIGGEST WORRY OF ME
COMING OUT OF HERE IS THAT I
WOULD BE TOO EMOTIONAL.
I SAID NO, IT SAY GAME, ALL
COMPARTMENTALIZED, NO, DAY
THREE, I WAS CRYING SO MUCH TO
MYSELF AND PEOPLE IN THE TRIBE.
YOU DON'T UNDERSTAND WHAT IS
GOES TO HAPPEN WHEN YOU ARE
HERE.
I RECOGNIZED THAT MY EMOTIONS
ARE MY GREATEST STRENGTH, AS A
THERAPIST I HAVE TO BE
EMPATHETIC AND EMOTIONAL BUT CAN
ALSO BE MY GREATEST WEAKNESS.
SO WHAT MAKES YOU GOOD ALSO
MAKES YOU BAD.
SO I REALLY LEARNED MORE ABOUT
THAT COMING OUT HERE FOR SURE.
I'M CURIOUS, HOW MANY PEOPLE,
BIG SHOT, HOW MANY PEOPLE WILL
ADMIT THAT THEY HAD A MOMENT
EVEN IF IT WAS JUST IN PRIVATE
WHETHER THERE WERE TEARS OR NOT,
IT WAS THE EQUIVALENT OF AN
EMOTIONAL CRY. WOW.
EVERY PERSON.
SO NOBODY CAN GET AWAY INTEREST
THAT.
OMAR, WHY IS THAT?
WHAT IS IT THAT HAPPENS THAT
BRINGS YOU TO THAT POINT?
I MEAN I ALMOST NEVER CRY IN
REAL LIFE SO THE FACT THAT I
CRIED SO MANY TIMES OUT HERE IS
OUTRAGEOUS, BUT I THINK IT
REALLY IS BECAUSE YOU ARE
STRIPPED TO THE CORE OF WHO YOU
ARE.
YOU HAVE NO COMFORT THAT WOULD
YOU NORMALLY HAVE IN REAL LIFE
AND YOUR EMOTIONAL SUPPORT
SYSTEM IS ABSENT AND YOU HAVE
NOTHING BUT TIME TO THINK.
AND YOU KNOW, SOMETIMES PAINFUL
MEMORIES FROM YOUR PAST COME
BACK.
AND YOU ARE IN AN ENVIRONMENT
WHERE YOU CAN EMBRACE THAT.
AND LET IT OUT.
AND SOMETIMES IT IS
GAME-RELATED.
SOMETIMES IT'S NOT.
BUT ARE YOU SO STRIPPED OF
EVERYTHING THAT EMOTIONS JUST
COMES OUT.
AND I CRIED MORE HERE THAN HAVE
I IN THE LAST TWO YEARS,
PROBABLY.
Probst: DREA HOW ABOUT FOR
YOU.
BEFORE YOU ANSWER, THIS IS MY
TAKE ON YOU.
AND REMEMBER I'M NOT ON THE
BEACHES WITH YOU.
BY DESIGN MY JOB IS TO JUST
OBSERVE THE THINGS I GET TO SEE
AND SEE WHAT I CAN LIRN.
AND NOT REALLY KNOW EVERYTHING
THAT IS GOING ON.
BUT YOU ALWAYS STRIKE ME AS A
LITTLE BIT LIKE THIS, BUT INSIDE
I THINK YOUR HEART IS LIKE THIS.
DID YOU HAVE YOUR MOMENTS.
YES, THAT'S ME.
AND I HAD PLENTY OF MOMENTS HERE
ON THIS ISLAND.
I CRIED AT NIGHT, JUST BY
MYSELF, WHEN PEOPLE WEREN'T HERE
I WAS STARVING.
I BARELY SLEPT.
IT WAS VERY EMOTIONAL FOR ME.
THIS WAS VERY HARD FOR ME, YEAH.
Probst: WE'RE GOING TO TAKE
ANOTHER QUICK BREAK, WHEN WE
COME BACK THOUGH I'M GOING TO
ASK OMAR SOME ANIMALS THAT HE
THINK DESCRIBES THE FINAL THREE.
BE RIGHT BACK WITH THE SURVIVOR.
COME ON IN WITH MORE CHAMPAGNE,
IT'S SURVIVOR 42 AFTERSHOW. UP
NEXT, WE CHECK BACK IN WITH OUR
FINAL THREE AND YOUR FIRST LOOK
AT SURVIVOR 43.
Probst: WELCOME BACK TO THE
SURVIVOR 42 AFTERSHOW.
I SHOULD CLEAR UP, IT'S NOT LIKE
WE HAVE A GIANT CATERING TEAM,
WHAT IS COOL ABOUT OUR TEAM IS
HALF THE PEOPLE DOING THIS RIGHT
NOW ARE THE SAME PEOPLE THAT
WERE OUT THERE ON THE BEACH WITH
ME.
THEY ARE OUR SHOOTERS, OUR AC'S,
OUR AUDIO TEAM, SURVIVOR IS THIS
BIG FAMILY WHICH IS WHY FOR ME
THIS IS THE MOST REAL REACTIONS
WE'RE EVER GOING TO GET.
SO AHMAR, LET'S HAVE SOME FUN.
YOU LOVE ANIMALS, LET'S NAME
SOME ANIMALS THAT DESCRIBE
MARYANNE, ROMEO AND MIKE.
OKAY.
SO MARYANNE IS DEFINITELY THE
AMAZON PARROT.
GOOGLE OF SIPGING, LAUGHING
IMMIGRATE-- IMITATING VOICES AND
SO CHEERY ALL OVER THE PLACE BUT
UNDERNEATH THAT THEY HAVE THE
INTELLIGENCE OF A TODDLER.
AND I DON'T MEAN THAT AS AN
INSULT TO YOU BUT FOR A BIRD FLA
IS PRETTY GOOD.
THEY ARE VERY INTELLIGENT
ANIMALS BUT THEY HAVE THAT FUN
AND GOOFY SIDE THAT ALWAYS KEEPS
YOU LAUGHING.
ROMEO IN THE GAME CUZ I DON'T
KNOW HIM OUTSIDE OF THE GAME
REMINDED ME OF A FLEDGE LING
BIRD LEAVING THE NEST BUT THEN
FALLS AND BREAKS ITS WINGS.
AND THEN I GOT TO TAKE IT IN AND
TRY TO HEAL IT AND WATCH HIM
GROW AND HE MATURED IN TO A FINALIST.
SO YOU KNOW, HE IS THE LITTLE
ROBIN THAT COULD.
MIKE, I DOBILITY KNOW, MAN-- .
Probst: JOB THAN, GIVE THE
MAN A MOMENT.
I FEEL LIKE MIKE IS LIKE-- OH
MY GOSH, LIKE A KOALA BEAR.
LIKE STRONG, SOLID, EATS THE
SAME THING EVERY DAY, A LITTLE
BIT CUDDLY BUT HE HAS A LITTLE
BIT OF THOSE CLAWS THAT YOU
DON'T SEE COMING UNTIL HE BLIND
SIDES YOU.
BUT ULTIMATELY HE HAS GOT A GOOD
HEART AND HE IS JUST A CUDDLY
BIG TEDDY BEAR.
Probst: ALL RIGHT, FOR THE
LAST COUPLE OF MINUTES HERE, I
JUST WANT TO CHECK BACK IN WITH
OUR FINAL THREE.
BECAUSE YOU HAVE BEEN THROUGH SO
MUCH.
YOU LITERALLY JUST FINISHED 26
OF THE MOST INTENSE DAYS OF YOUR LIFE.
THEN YOU FACED YOUR JURY AND
THEY GRILLED YOU.
AND NOW WE HAVE A WINNER.
SO THERE IS NO DOUBT YOU ARE
GOING HOME KNOWING, YOU ARE
GOING TO GO HOME TRYING TO KEEP
A SECRET, HOPEFULLY.
SO ROMEO, WHAT IS THE FEELING
YOU HAVE A LITTLE FOOD IN YOUR
STOMACH, 96 INSTEAD OF -9D 5.
WHAT IS YOUR FEELING, ARE YOU
PROUD OF YOURSELF?
YES, I'M VERY PROUD OF MYSELF.
BECAUSE LIKE I SAID BEFORE I
CAME HERE FOR THE EXPERIENCE.
AND I GOT THE WHOLE EXPERIENCE.
I WENT AS FAR AS ANYONE CAN GO
IN THIS GAME.
AND I HAVE NO HARD FEELINGS.
IT IS A GAME.
I STILL LOVE THESE PEOPLE AND I
STILL WANT TO HANG OUT WITH THEM
AND I FEEL LIKE I GREW OUT HERE
AND OMAR'S REFERENCE, YES, I
WILL TAKE THAT.
YOU KNOW, I WAS VERY SCARED,
VERY PARANOID, AND IN THE END I
WON THAT FINAL IMMUNITY
CHALLENGE AND I THOUGHT I WON.
IN THE GAME OF LIFE I FEEL LIKE
I WON CONDITIONS CAN'T DID FOR
MORE THAN THAT, RIGHT?
NO.
HOW ABOUT YOU, HERE IS WHAT
MI WONDERING.
YOU GOT VERY QUIET.
I DON'T KNOW T COWS J BE THE
PIZZA ARE YOU PUTTING DOWN.
BUT ARE YOU GOOD WITH THIS?
I'M EXTREMELY GOOD WITH IT.
GOOD THINGS WILL HAPPEN WITH
THAT MONEY.
QUITE FRANKLY, NOT THAT I DON'T
WANT THAT MONEY BUT I DON'T
REALLY NEED THE MONEY.
AS I TOLD EVERYBODY, I'M HAPPY
IN LIFE.
I HAVE MY FEE AN SAIRKS I HAVE
MY KIDS.
I'M ALREADY RICH.
SHE'S A YOUNG GIRL SETTING OUT.
AND I KNOW GOOD THINGS ARE GOING
TO HAPPEN WITH THAT MONEY, SO I
AM EXTREMELY FIEFN WITH EVERYTHING.
AND HONESTLY, I REALLY LIKE
EVERYBODY IN THIS TENT, THERE IS
NOT A MEAN PERSON HERE.
Probst: WHICH BRINGS US TO
YOU MARYANNE.
I REMEMBER MEETING YOU.
I REMEMBER THE FIRST TIME WE
SPOKE AND I REMEMBER THINKS
SHE'S GOT TO BE ON THE SHOW, SHE
IS JUST TOO FUN, TOO ENERGETIC,
HER SMILE IS TOO AMAZING.
WHAT I DIDN'T KNOW ABOUT YOU OR
DIDN'T EXPECT ABOUT YOU IS HOW
GOOD YOU WOULD BE.
I THINK YOU WERE REALLY GOOD AT
THIS GAME.
I THINK YOU WORKED PEOPLE AT THE
RIGHT TIME.
I THINK YOU USED YOUR CHARM
MAYBE MORE THAN YOU ARE SAYING.
I THINK YOU WERE A VERY
IMPRESSIVE WINNER AND AS YOU SIT
HERE NOW, KNOWING THAT YOU HAVE
A MILLION DOLLARS, YOU ARE THE
WINNER OF SURVIVOR 42, AS YOU
SAID, ONE OF ONLY 40 WINNERS FOR
A SHOW THAT HAS BEEN ON 21 YEARS.
OH MY GOD.
Probst: HOW DO YOU FEEL
RIGHT NOW?
CLOSE THIS OUT?
IT STILL FEELS LIKE THIS
ISN'T HAPPENING.
LIKE I FEEL AS IF I ALWAYS KNEW
THAT I WAS GOING TO GO ON TIS
SHOW.
BUT I REMEMBER LIKE GOING AND
LITERALLY LEAVING AND WRITING
NIE BUCKET LIST AND HAVING MY
SISTER LOOK AT IT AND SAY WHY
ISN'T WINNING ON THIS BUCKET
LIST.
AND I TRULY DIDN'T THINK I WAS
GOING TO WIN.
SHE IS LIKE YOU ARE GOING INTO
THIS GAME THINKING YOU CAN'T
WIN, YEAH, LIKE I WAS ALREADY
THINK BEING THE JURY, AND WHICH
I WITH WEAR TO THIS ONE AND THIS
ONE.
BECAUSE UNTIL THE DAY BEFORE I
CAME OUT HERE, I DIDN'T THINK I
HAD THE ABILITY TO WIN.
AND IT IS LIKE, TO COME OUT HERE
AND THEN TO PLAY A GAME THEN
AFTER TO PLAY CLEARLY ONE OF THE
SLOPPY GAME ACCORDING TO THE
JURY MEMBERS WHICH IS FINE BUT
THEN TO STILL PULL IT OUT AND BE
ABLE TO WIN T IS LIKE WHEN I
TOLD YOU HOW I FEEL LIKE I'M
DREESMING, IT FEELS LIKE I'M
DREAMING RIGHT NOW.
Probst: I'M REALLY PROUD
THAT YOU WON.
YOU ARE A GREAT WINNER.
I THINK YOU ARE GOING TO
REPRESENT SURVIVOR WELL.
YES, YOU ARE.
OH MY GOSH.
Probst: I'M SO HAPPY THAT
YOU DID WHAT YOU DID TO GET OUT HERE.
BECAUSE I KNOW IT TOOK A LOT FOR
US TO GET HERE.
I KNOW IT TOOK A LOT FOR YOU TO
GET HERE AND YOUR FAMILY, YOUR
FRIENDS, WHOEVER SUPPORTED YOU
TO GET OUT HERE.
I HOPE YOU FEEL IT WAS WORTH IT.
I LOVED WATCHING YOU PLAY, THIS
WAS A GREAT SEASON OF SURVIVOR
AND TO THE PLAYERS, THE NONJURY
WHO AREN'T HERE, WE ARE SORRY
YOU AREN'T HERE.
WE WISH YOU COULD BE HERE AS WELL.
THIS HAS BEEN THE BEST TIME IN
THE JUNGLES OF FIJI AND TO ALL
OF YOU WITHOUT CONTINUE TO WATCH
SURVIVOR, WE THANK YOU.
IT'S NOT LIKE YOU ARE FANS, WE
WHERE A TRIAD, SOME PEOPLE
PRODUCE, SOME PEOPLE PLAY, SOME
PEOPLE WATCH AND END UP PLAYING
AND COME BACK WATCHING.
BUT IT IS ALL THIS BIG
FAMILIMENT AND WE'VE HAD A BLAST
AND I LOOK FORWARD TO BRINGING
YOU SURVIVOR 43 NEXT.
HERE'S YOUR FIRST LOOK.
IT WASN'T A MATTER OF IF I
WAS GOING TO PLAY SURVIVOR.
IT WAS A MATTER OF WHEN.
I WENT FROM BEING IN A GANG
- TO BEING IN A Ph.
- D PROGRAM AT DUKE.
I JUST WANT TO SHOW THAT YOU CAN
DO ANYTHING YOU WANT.
I AM SCARED TO DEATH.
IT IS DEFINITELY GOING TO BE THE
HARDEST CHALLENGE OF MY ENTIRE LIFE.
DOES SURVIVOR MOVE FAST?
WE WHERE ON A JET.
IN THE OPERATING ROOM WHEN
THINGS GET REALLY INTENSE,
THAT'S WHEN I GET TO BE MY BEST.
SURVIVOR IS THE ULTIMATE GAME
AND HUMAN TEST.
THERE IS NOT ONE WAY TO WIN.
IF YOU HAD TO TAKE IN ALL OF THE
DATA AND KNOW WHEN TO STRIKE.
GROWING UP IN A TOUGH
ENVIRONMENT, THERE IS SOME CODES
TO GROW UP BY, I'M AN ETH KAL PERSON.
THERE ARE THINGS I WOULDN'T
CROSS THE LINE ON, LIKE I DON'T
THINK I WOULD-- YOU KNOW WHAT,
NO, THERE IS REALLY NOTHING I
WOULDN'T DO.
I LIVE TO GET RADICAL, THAT
SAY MANTRA OF MINE, I HAVE IT
TATTOOED ON MY BUTT CHEEK.
ONE THING DO I AS A
PSYCHOLOGIST IS GET PEOPLE TO DO
THINGS THEY DON'T WANT TO DO.
I'M HERE TO BE THE YOUNGEST
EVER IN SURVIVOR HISTORY, WRITE
THIS DOWN, AT ALL COSTS.
IN THE GAME OF SURVIVOR YOU
WILL KNOW VICTORY.
YOU WILL KNOW PAIN.
BRING IT ON.
LET'S ALL VOM MORE CHAMPAGNE.
WHO CAN I GIVE SOME TOO.
ALL RIGHT.
LET'S DO IT.
WOW.
IF YOU WANT TO BID ON PROPS
FROM THIS SEASON OF SURVIVOR GO
TO SURVIVOR AUCTIONS.COM,
PROCEEDS GO TO STAND UP TO
CANCER.
WHAT ARE YOU WAITING FOR, APPLY
TO BE ON SURVIVOR.